<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anti-Paræus, or, A treatise in the defence of the royall right of kings against Paræus and the rest of the anti-monarchians, whether Presbyterians or Jesuits. Wherein is maintained the unlawfulnesse of opposing and taking up arms against the Prince, either by any private subject, inferiour magistrate, the states of the Kingdom, or the Pope of Rome. Confirm'd from the dictate of nature, the law of nations, the civill and canon law, the sacred scriptures, ancient fathers, and Protestant divines. Delivered formerly in a determination in the divinity schooles in Cambridge, April the 9th. 1619. And afterwards enlarged for the presse by learned Dr. Owen. Now translated and published to confirme men in their loyalty to their king, by R.M. Master in Arts.</title>
            <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O703</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6219</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834780</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834780</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39316</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39316)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 393:5 or 1818:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anti-Paræus, or, A treatise in the defence of the royall right of kings against Paræus and the rest of the anti-monarchians, whether Presbyterians or Jesuits. Wherein is maintained the unlawfulnesse of opposing and taking up arms against the Prince, either by any private subject, inferiour magistrate, the states of the Kingdom, or the Pope of Rome. Confirm'd from the dictate of nature, the law of nations, the civill and canon law, the sacred scriptures, ancient fathers, and Protestant divines. Delivered formerly in a determination in the divinity schooles in Cambridge, April the 9th. 1619. And afterwards enlarged for the presse by learned Dr. Owen. Now translated and published to confirme men in their loyalty to their king, by R.M. Master in Arts.</title>
                  <author>Owen, David, d. 1623.</author>
                  <author>Mossom, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 91, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Stephen Bulkley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed: R. Mossom.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing M2859 on UMI microfilm set "Early English books, 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pareus, David, 1548-1622. --  Quaestiones controversae theologicae, de jure regum et principum .. adversus Bellarminum.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANTI-PARÆUS, OR, A Treatiſe in the Defence of the Royall Right of <hi>KINGS:</hi> Againſt <hi>Paraeus</hi> and the reſt of the Anti-Monarchians, whether Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians or Jeſuits.</p>
            <p>Wherein is maintained the unlawfulneſſe of oppoſing and taking up Arms againſt the Prince, either by any private Subject, inferiour Magiſtrate, the States of the Kingdom, or the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Confirm'd from the dictate of Nature, the Law of Nations, the Civill and Canon Law, the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Ancient Fathers, and Proteſtant Divines.</p>
            <p>Delivered formerly in a Determination in the Divinity Schooles in CAMBRIDGE, <hi>April</hi> the 9<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1619. And afterwards enlarged for the Preſſe by Learned D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. OWEN.</p>
            <p>Now Tranſlated and Publiſhed to confirme Men in their Loyalty to their King, By <hi>R. M.</hi> Maſter in Arts.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>York</hi> by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THOMAS GLEMHAM KNIGHT, Collonell Generall and Governour of the CITY of YORK,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A Breſt Fortified with Loyalty is the CITY of Refuge this Worke flyes to, whereof your Noble Selfe being Governour, it craves with Boldneſſe a Gracious Entrance, and doubts not of your Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Protection. If my particular Duty did not engage me, your Noble Worth would ſoone Invite me to Dedicate my Labours to your Honourable Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage; for who ſhall better Patronize that Worke whoſe Subject is Loyalty, than he who is a Loyall Subject? who better
<pb facs="tcp:39316:3"/>encourage the Pen in the Cauſe of Kings, than he, who with Glory hath engaged his Sword in the Kings Cauſe? But Sir, I will not detract from your Worth by preſuming to declare it; being a thing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter known by your Actions, than I can expreſſe by Words. Onely this; whileſt this CITY gloryes ſo much in being under your Government, the Souldiers under your Command, give the Scholler leave to glory in being under your Patronage. Goe on Sir in your Loyalty to the Crown, and God ſhall Crown your Loyalty, let your aime ſtill be Gods Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and your Soveraignes Honour; and that ſhall make for your Soules Happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and this Kingdomes Peace. Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>York, <date>March the 10. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt humbly Devoted Servant, <hi>R. MOSSOM.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader, wiſhing Loyalty and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>COurteous Reader,</hi> If thou enquireſt after the Author, know he was a Man of ſo much Piety as to write nothing but what his conſcience told him was the Truth; and of ſo much Learning, as to maintaine the Truth he writ. Howſoever, then, thou doſt cenſure the weakneſſe of the Tranſlatour, yet caſt no aſperſion upon the Authour. Let him Reſt, who is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to his Eternall Reſt, and hath left this Worke as a Lecture of Loyalty, which if thou readeſt ſhall either helpe to convince thy Conſcience or (without Repentance) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thy Soule.</p>
            <p>Take heed therfore to thy ſelf, that whilſt thou reſiſts a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious King thou reſiſt not the Holy Spirit too, who is the Spirit of Truth. It is as well out of love to thy Soule, as du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to my Soveraigne, that I have publiſhed this preſent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe in thy Mothers Tongue. That if thou haſt lift up thine hand againſt thy King in Rebellion, thou mayſt lift it up again to God in Prayer for Pardon; and that as thou deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to profeſſe thy ſelf a true Chriſtian, thou mayſt declare thy ſelfe a true Subject. This Worke was written above twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares ſince, and therefore free from the prejudice of the Times, envy and flattery. And know ſuch hath bin my faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in the Tranſlation, that I have rather choſen to loſe of the Luſtre of the Stile, than to detract from the Sincerity
<pb facs="tcp:39316:4"/>and Truth of the Matter. The Language is plaine, being intended (eſpecially) for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar, who moſt need inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this leſſon of Loyalty, their diſobedience ariſing from their Weakneſſe, though others from their Wilfulneſſe, whoſe Judgement will be the greater. Let me prevaile with thee <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> to lay aſide all private Reſpects, which may prejudice the Truth of this Worke, for Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> rule is moſt firme, <hi>quamdiu blanditur ſibi &amp; dulcis eſt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas amara eſt veritas,</hi> Truth will taſte bitter to that Palate which pleaſeth it ſelfe with the ſweetneſſe of Impiety. Do thou with as much Sincerity read, as the Authour writ, and when thou art convinct in judgement how great an Impiety it is to riſe up againſt a moſt Wicked Prince; conſider what an height of Impiety they ariſe to, who riſe up againſt a moſt Pious King? if they receive to themſelves Damnation who reſiſt a <hi>Nero,</hi> a perſecuting Emperour, what ſhall they receive to themſelves who take up Arms againſt our <hi>Charles,</hi> a moſt gracious Soveraigne? if it be a Sinne to oppoſe that King who violates; how great a Sinne is it to injure thy King who protects the Laws of the Kingdome? I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne thee longer from that Satisfaction thou ſhalt receive in peruſing this Booke; there thou ſhalt find all the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary's objections fully anſwered; the truth it ſelfe fully clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; be obedient to the Truth and I doubt not but thou wilt be loyall to thy King. If otherwiſe, take this with thee at thy Farewell. <hi>Qui inſurgit in Chriſtum Domini, inſurgit in Dominum Chriſti:</hi> he that riſeth up againſt the Anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord, riſeth up againſt the Lord of the Anoynted.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:4"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>AFter that the People of Iſrael had eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the darkeneſſe of Ægypt, and the Wilderneſſe, they were infeſted from the Eaſt by the Ammonites, from the Weſt by the Philiſtines, from the North by the Aſſyrians, and from the South by the Ægyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians; So even now the Faithfull Flocke, is every where from every place Impugned, whilſt Tyranny rageth, Hereſie prevaileth, Schiſme overſpreadeth, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie deceiveth, and all Impiety encreaſeth, againſt the ſoundneſſe of Faith, the fervour of Charity and the integrity of Life; to the ſeducing (if it were poſſible) the very Elect of God, whom Chriſt hath committed alſo, to the Truſt of Kings, by whoſe Laws the Church is fortified, and by whoſe Arms ſhe is defended; againſt the incurſion of the Enemyes, the perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Hereſie, the diviſions of Schiſme, the flattery's of Hypocriſie, and the corruption of Manners. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Miniſters leave no ſtone unmoved, that they may exclude the King from the charge committed to him, which they endeavour, by denying the Authority Regall in matters Eccleſiaſticall, by taking away the
<pb facs="tcp:39316:5"/>Royall Power in matters Politicall, and by uſurping the Soveraignty in both.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Authority Eccleſiaſticall is deny'd, by the Papiſts.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtians ought to be ſubject to Kings as Supreame; that is true indeed, but in thoſe things only which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the State Politicke.</hi> So Bellarm. de Pontif. l. 1. c. 7.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>By the Diſciplinarian</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Civill Power is referr'd to things Earthly and Temporall; but the Eccleſiaſticall is referr'd to things Spirituall, and which appertaine to the Worſhip of God: from whence it is, that the Eccleſiaſticall Power is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſtiled</hi> jus poli, <hi>the right of Heaven, the Civill,</hi> jus ſoli, <hi>the right of Earth</hi> So Bucan loco. 43. Sect. 5.</p>
                  <p>Majeſty muſt creepe on the ground, whilſt thoſe our Spirituall Maſters, placed in the Clouds, doe from high behold it below them, and diſpiſe it as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was of another mind,<note place="margin">In quaeſt. mixt. <hi>35.</hi>
                     </note> when he taught, <hi>That the King hath the Image of God, as the Biſhop the Image of Chriſt,</hi> yea, by ſo much the more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently doth he expreſſe the Divine Image, by how much the glory of a Judge is more excellent, and his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty more illuſtrious then that of the Prieſt. I appeale to your own Conſciences (good Men) what and how great thinke you was the Power of ancient Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours? by whoſe ſacred command Churches have been dedicated, Biſhops inveſted, the Clergy exempted,
<pb facs="tcp:39316:5"/>and Synods aſſembled, in which themſelves ſate Preſidents, and confirmed their Decrees; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by eſtabliſhing the Faith, overthrowing Hereſie, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iging Clergy and Laity to the worſhip of God, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing all things requiſite for the excerciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ordering by their Laws the forme of outward Worſhip; and all this they did <hi>by a lawfull power,</hi> as <hi>Socrates in prolog. l.</hi> 5. and as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expreſly and elegantly, <hi>de civit. Deil.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 24. yea to the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of humane things, and neceſſity of the Church, as one of the Popes himſelfe has confeſt. <hi>Leo ad pulche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimam Auguſtam,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>Humane things can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe be ſafe, than as they pertaine to the Divine Profeſsion, and be defended by Regall and Prieſtly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Power Civill is taken away by the Papiſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Supreame Princes are obnoxious to the Laws, by all Law, Naturall, Nationall, and Poſitive; and it is in the power of the Common-wealth to require againe the authority it has committed to the Prince for the publike good, and to exauthorize the King if he ſhall evilly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</hi> So Parſon. in Doleman. par. 1. c. 4.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>By the Diſciplinarian.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Tyranny and unjuſt Violence of the Superiour Magiſtrate ought to be reſtrain'd by the ordinary power; which in every Polity is either the Inferiour Magiſtrate,
<pb facs="tcp:39316:6"/>or the conſent of the People. So</hi> Paraus <hi>in Epiſt, ad Rom. c.</hi> 13. <hi>queſt.</hi> 4. <hi>prop.</hi> 2.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Soveraignty is uſurped in both, by the Papiſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judgement concerning the King belongs to the Pope, to whom is committed the charge of Religion; therefore it is the Popes right to judge the King to be depoſed, or not to be depoſed.</hi> So Bellarmine de pont. l. 5 c. 7.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>By the Diſciplinarian.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Presbytery is erected in the Church as Chriſts Tribunall: Who then ſhall exempt Kings and Princes from their Soveraignty not humane but divine, and not be guilty of Treaſon againſt the Majeſty of Chriſt? So Beza de preſb. p.</hi> 116. Hence forwards, let Kings ceaſe their care of Religion, the Pope will undertake that charge, and ſo will the Presbytery; the Pope in his Kingdome, the Presbytery in it's Dominion. If any Secular Prince ſhall put in his ſickle, to cut down this ſtanding corne of the Popes, or this new-ſprung hearbe of the Presbytery, he ſhall not eſcape unpuniſhed; the Popes thunderings, and the Conſiſtoryes lightnings ſhall purſue him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the People equally bewitched with errour, one where aſſiſts the Pope, another where the Presbytery, but every where reſiſts the King, that he may learne poore King at length,</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To hold his Scepter, and to lay it down</l>
                     <l>At's Peopl's favour, and at's Peopl's frown.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:39316:6"/>
                  <p>About foure yeares ſince when according to the order of our Univerſity, (after I had taken the degree of Doctor) it was impoſed upon me to determine a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie in Divinity; my duty did require me to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the free and abſolute Power of Kings againſt <hi>David Paraeus,</hi> and the Anti-monarchians. Which aſſertion, when I had intended to have kept reſerved; provoked by the raſhneſſe of an heady young man in <hi>Oxford,</hi> I have preſented to publike view, having been more ſeverely examined, and more largely explained. I appeale to thy own Conſcience, whoſoever thou art (O Chriſtian and Faithfull Subject) whether doth this uſurped Tyranny over the Lords anoynted ones, favour at all of the Spirit of Truth? is not this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording concord of falſe Brethren, fit to be committed to the fire? fit to be exploded with the unanimous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all Chriſtians? the Fathers of old both thought and writ more holily, both according to the Preſcript of the divine Law, and Rule of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>Tertullian. <hi>God alone it is, in whoſe power onely Kings are, to whom they are ſecond, after whom they are firſt, above all men, before all Gods. in Apologet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Agapetus. <hi>The Emperour is equall to every man in the naturall eſſence of Body, but equall to a God preſident over all in the powerfull excellency of Dignity; for he has not on Earth, any higher than himſelfe. Therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooves him, as a God, not to be carryed away with wrath, as a Mortall, not to be lifted up with pride; for though he be honour'd with the divine likeneſſe, yet is he fram'd of the earthly duſt whereby he is taught, that he preſerve a juſt equallity towards all. Paraenet. ad Juſtin. Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:39316:7"/>
                  <p>Gregorius Magnus. <hi>Therefore is there power given to the Emperour from Heaven, over all men on Earth; that the way to Heaven might be laid open, and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpread, that ſo the earthly Kingdome might be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to the Heavenly. Epiſt.</hi> 91. <hi>l.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>This moſt ſacred Majeſty which God himſelfe hath ordained, Chriſt confirmed, and the Orthodoxe Church perpetually reverenced, I now endeavour to vindicate from the injury of ſeditious men; and that with ſolid Reaſons drawn even from Nature, the Law of Nations, the Civill Law, Canon Law, the word of God, the ſayings of the Fathers, and the writing of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. All which are ſo truly, fairely, and ſincerely alledged; that I neither feare the Judgement of the Reader, nor the calumny of the Adverſary. Thou pious Reader, and Loyall Subject, live well, and fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <l>If ought thou know'ſt that better is to me impart;</l>
                        <l>If not, uſe theſe with me, and ſo thou friendly art.</l>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:7"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The Queſtion ſtated, Pag. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Terms explain'd, pag. <hi>2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Agreement of Presbyterians and Jeſuits, pag. <hi>3.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The foure Propoſitions of <hi>Paraeus</hi> are refuted.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> the Excommunication of Kings, pag. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> the Power of the inferiour Magiſtrate, pag. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> the duty of a private Man, pag. <hi>47.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> private revenge in caſe of neceſsity, pag. <hi>57.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The abſolute Power of Kings is confirm'd.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>From</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>the Dictate of Nature, pag. <hi>68.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>the Law of Nations, pag. <hi>69.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>the Civill Law, pag. <hi>74.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>the Canon Law, pag. <hi>77.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>the Holy Scriptures pag. <hi>78.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>the Ancient Fathers, pag. <hi>84.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>the Proteſtant Divines, pag. <hi>85.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39316:8"/>
            <head>ANTI-PARAEVS. <note place="margin">The queſtion Stated.</note>
               <hi>The Poſition:</hi> It is not lawfull to reſiſt the King, violating the Fundamentall Laws of the Kingdome.</head>
            <p>DIvers Men in this our Age, have handled this controverſie Divers Waies, whilſt the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificians contend to have the Royall Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubmit to the Roman Purple, the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians to the States of the Kingdome, and in ſome caſes to the provoked Multitude; and the Proteſtants to God alone. <hi>David Paraeus,</hi> A Palatine Divine, in the Year 1612. writ very elegantly coucer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lawfull Right of Kings, in the behalfe of the then Soveraigne and moſt potent Prince, King of Great <hi>Brittain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> againſt the Papall Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, againſt <hi>Bellarmine, Becanus,</hi> and other Popiſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites of the ſame mold. The <hi>Printer</hi> Dedicated that Tract to the ſame Soveraigne, in which the foundation of that Pontifician Tower is raſed, the ſophiſticall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> are confuted; the vain Arguments of <hi>Becanus</hi> refell'd, and the cunning Impoſtures of the Canoniſts forcibly retorted. Yet, as if he had drunke deep of the<note n="*" place="margin">A Lake that Wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevah and Lauſama.</note> Lemanian Lake, he brandiſhes the inferiour
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39316:9"/>Magiſtrates Sword, againſt Kings and greateſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and affords no leſſe dangerous, than impious Arms, to the confuſed and incompoſed multitude, and this in many parts of that Tract, out of which receive theſe few ſelected.</p>
            <p>The violence and tyranny of the Superiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ought to be reſtrained by the Ordinary Power, which in every Polity is either the inferiour Magiſtrate, or the conſent of the People. This <hi>David Paraeus</hi> has <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 4. <hi>Tract. de poteſt. civ. rat.</hi> 1. Againſt <hi>Bellarmine, Becanus, Danaeus, Paraeus,</hi> and the reſt ſo devoutly addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Popedome, or the Presbytery. I confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aver, That neither the Roman Biſhop, the States of a Kingdome, nor the Tumultuous Commons, have any power over Kings which offend, or violate the Laws which they call Fundamentall; and this I ſhall manifeſt and evince by many ſtrong Reaſons, that I may give ſome light to the weaker ſort of Men, diſtracted with variety of Opinions; that as Men placed in a Watch-Tower, they may a far off diſcover; or as Men ſayling in the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they may without danger eſcape thoſe gulfes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and Whirle-Pooles of Falſhoods, with which the Writings of Papiſts and Puritans do plentifully abound. But in the firſt place to the taking away all ambiguity, I will explain the Terms of the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Terms of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on explained.</note> I call him <hi>King</hi> who hath a Supreame Power, ſubject to none. In the Word <hi>Reſiſt,</hi> I comprehend all Power of gainſaying, all commotion or confederacy againſt the Royall Majeſty, a <hi>Violator of the Fundamentall Laws,</hi> is, (according to the Theologicall Politicks) ſuch an one as doth overthrow either all, or the chiefeſt eſtabliſht Laws of the Common-wealth. The Puritan-Papiſts tell us,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39316:9"/>the Fundamentall Laws, are (I know not what) contracts or conditionall Covenants, betwixt the King and the People, entred and eſtabliſht by Oath at the Kings firſt Inauguration; which being broken, they will have the People free, and looſe from all Bonds of Allegiance and Religion to their Soveraignes, the Kings being <hi>ipſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> null and deveſted of all authority. As if that Sacred Majeſty given by God, were confer'd by the People, and that upon certain conditionall Laws; at whoſe pleaſure it is to be reſigned. Which madneſſe, I will clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute from the Dictate of Nature, the Law of Nations, the Civill Law, Canon Law, from Sacred Scripture, Orthodox Fathers, and the moſt famous Paſtors of the reformed Church; who, as they have bid adieu to the Popedome, ſo have they not ſworn to the Dictates of the novell Presbytery. But firſt give me leave to ſhew the ſeditious agreement of Papiſts and Puritans againſt the Majeſty of Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt the Majeſty of Kings.</note> 
               <hi>Robert Bellarmine</hi> an excellently Learned <hi>Cardinal,</hi> moſt accurately skilfull in unlooſing the Knots of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; yet <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Pontif.</hi> he doth ſo involve this power of reſtraining Kings with ſo many ſubtilties; that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives no better ſtile from <hi>Carerius</hi> than Atheiſt and Politician. Yet, under the Maske of <hi>Mathaeus Tortus</hi> doth he impoſe the ſame upon the Engliſh Papiſts, as the foundation of the Catholique Faith. And in a Tract, concerning the Temporall Power of the Pope, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Barclay,</hi> he concludes the ſame clearly and briefly from many Arguments, reduced to foure heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from the authority of ſome Writers, <hi>Italian, French, Spaniſh, German</hi> and <hi>Engliſh;</hi> of whom <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh is the firſt, <hi>Nicholas Sanders</hi> the laſt, he the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39316:10"/>Head, this the Tayle of that Beaſt in the <hi>Revelations.</hi> Secondly, from good Scripture, but bad interpretation. Thirdly, from politicall Reaſons. Laſtly, from Examples.</p>
            <p>Of all them which ſtand on the Presbyterian ſide, <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi> is the moſt Learned, and in reſolving controverſies the moſt perſpicacious. After thoſe many and weariſome labours againſt the Pontificians and Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, when he was now grown old; he put forth his Chriſtian Politie as his laſt work, and in <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6. he propounds (as he calls it) this noble queſtion: <hi>whether Chriſtian Men, and Pious Subjects may with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience change and abrogate a conſtituted Polity, and chuſe to themſelves another? He anſwers,</hi> That, <hi>the Supream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate violating the Fandameutall Laws of the Kingdom, may be depoſed by godly Subjects, and that with a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> And <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6. he affirmes; That, <hi>Judgement upon the Superiour Magiſtrate, who exceeds the bounds of his duty, or performs not his duty as he ought; belongs to the States of the Kingdome:</hi> And this he endeavours to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie with a ſoure ſquare Army, like to the Macedonian Phalans. Firſt from Politicall Reaſons. Secondly, from the authority of Gods Word. Thirdly, from the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Prudent; namely, <hi>John Calvin, Brutus Junius,</hi> and <hi>George Bucanan.</hi> Laſtly, from Examples, and thoſe of the Ancients; namely, the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians, Athenians,</hi> and <hi>Romans:</hi> alſo thoſe of later times: namely, <hi>French, Spaniſh, Germans, Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch.</hi> And againſt <hi>Bellarmine, Controverſ.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7. he confeſſeth plainly, That, <hi>the King which is an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke ought to be depeſed; but that, not by the Biſhop of Rome; but by the States of the Kingdeme.</hi> Thoſe things which have been occaſionally, here and there toucht up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39316:10"/>by others, are all collected into one ſumme, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted into Method by <hi>David Paraeus;</hi> which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in foure Propoſitions; each of which I will ſet down, leaſt I ſhould ſeem to let any thing eſcape.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>The firſt Propoſition.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Biſhops and Paſtors may and ought (upon the conſent of the Church) deliver up the contumacious Magiſtrates unto</hi> Satan <hi>untill they do repent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">firſt Propeſition of <hi>Paraeus</hi> confuted,</note>In theſe few words, do lurke not a few errors. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy is a Law Terme, which the Lawyers define to be; a Diſobedience againſt the Superiour; as often as the Subject, being cited in a due courſe of Law, doth not appeare, doth not obey, or depart without Licence. The Supreame Magiſtrate, being inferiour to God alone, is not ſubject to Man, and therefore neither can, nor ought to iucur the guilt of Contumacy. <hi>Some ſpeak with good reaſon</hi> (ſaith <hi>John</hi> of Paris) <hi>that, not every offendor is a fit matter upon which or can work with effect. but that offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor whe is a Subject,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Kings can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be ſayd to be contumaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> 
                     <hi>and therefore the foreſaid power has not effection the Offender, unleſſe when ſubjection is preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; which makes a Man to be a fit matter, upon which the Keyes may have their Act with effect.</hi> de poteſt. Regia &amp; Papaſi. c. 13.</p>
                  <p>A King in his Kingdom is not ſubject to the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39316:11"/>Juriſdiction, as it is penall and coercive,<note place="margin">How the King is not ſubject to the power of the Keyes.</note> but is ſuperiour in Order of Power; as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirm's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly. Moſes <hi>was in the midſt betwixt</hi> Aaron <hi>and God,</hi> Aaron <hi>in the midſt betwixt</hi> Moſes <hi>and the people, &amp;c.</hi> In <hi>Exod. queſt.</hi> 10. Thoſe Biſhops therfore and Supercilious Paſtors, who ſend out their citation, or put forth their accuſation againſt their Prince, are impious againſt God, whoſe Ordinance they reſiſt; ſeditious againſt the King, ouer whoſe ſoueraignty they inſult; Traytors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Common wealth, whoſe Peace they diſturbe. I beleive <hi>Paraeus</hi> can neuer ſhew, where any one of the Apoſtles ſate Judge of Princes. <hi>I read the Æpoſtles ſtood to be Judged, but I never read they ſtood Judging,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard, de conſiderat. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The conſent of the Church not required in the act of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Whereas he ſaith, <hi>(upon conſent of the Church)</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt he doth but catch at popular Applauſe, by ſubjecting Princes to the cenſure of the Paſtors, and the Paſtors to the Judgement of the People. The Apoſtles had the power of the Keyes from Chriſt, and the Biſhops have it from the Apoſtles, without reſervation of the Churches conſent. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> cals this power, <hi>the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall judgment; de corrept. &amp; grat. c.</hi> 15. and <hi>Beza</hi> himſelfe hath exploded this <hi>Conſent</hi> out of a well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Church, as <hi>wicked, dangerous, and diſſonant to the Word of God. in Epiſt.</hi> 83.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To deliver unto Satan]</hi> (which he improperly attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to excommunication) was an extraordinary po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer granted to the Apoſtles for a time:<note place="margin">What is meant by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sathan.</note> according to the more commonly received opinion of Ancient and Moderne Divines. Conſult S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon that 1. <hi>Tim. c.</hi> 1. S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5. <hi>hom.</hi> 15. S. <hi>Aug,</hi> againſt the letters of <hi>Petilian. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. S. <hi>Hierome, Bede,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39316:11"/>Theodoret, Occumenius, Theophylact</hi> and <hi>Sedulius:</hi> all upon that (1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 5.) of the Apoſtles <hi>to deliver to Satan</hi> which all of them doe underſtand, to be meant of that corporall affliction, which the Apoſtles did inflict: not by the power of the Keyes, but by the power of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miracles. To which I adde the Divines of later times, and thoſe of better note and ſounder judgement, <hi>Thomas Bilſon</hi> lately Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter, Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Thomas Eraſtus,</hi> and <hi>Benedict Aretius;</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded</hi> (ſaith that Reverend Biſhop) <hi>that</hi> S. Paul <hi>in revenging that wickednes, would have ſome footſtep re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine of that wonderfull power and virtue, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Chriſt to revenge impiety; whereby the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſo great a wickednes, might hereafter ſeem dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the reſt,</hi> &amp;c. in his perpetuall government of the Church, <hi>c.</hi> 8.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>The Apoſtles</hi> (ſaith Peter Martyr) <hi>had the Devills ſubject to them, and by them they might ſometimes puniſh offendors to the furtherance of their ſalvation, therefore to whom this gift is not imparted, they ought wholy to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from the exerciſe thereof. locor. com. claſ.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 9.</q> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>The power of delivering unto Sathan,</hi> (as <hi>Eraſtus</hi> hath it) <hi>which was given to</hi> S. Paul, <hi>was not ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the Church, that it ſhould become an ordinary po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Confirm. Theſ. lib.</hi> 41. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</q> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>To deliver unto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than was a power delivered unto the Apoſtles</hi> (ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retius</hi>) <hi>of puniſhing the notoriouſly contumacious, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ceaſed.</hi> Upon the 1 <hi>Tim. c.</hi> 1.</q> From the miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous power of the Apoſtles to the ordinary juriſdiction of Paſtors, is a moſt frivolous conſequence, for what did extraordinarily belong to the Apoſtles, had its end with the Apoſtles: but grant we that this <hi>delivering unto
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39316:12"/>Satan,</hi> has no other ſignification, but that of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication;
it will not from hence follow, That it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for Paſtors to exclude the Supreame Magiſtrates from converſe with their Subjects. The preſcripts of the Goſpell, of making the wicked aſhamed, avoyding the company of the Scandalous, and rebuking the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, whilſt there was no Man in the Church, intruſted with the Sword, to the revenge of evill doers; are not raſhly to be applyed to the diſgracing, deſerting, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buking the Magiſtrate.<note place="margin">Note.</note> For the rule is, Thoſe things which by the Prophets and Apoſtles are ſet down in Generall, ought not to be preſſed to the everting thoſe things which are commanded by them in particular. God in the Law and in the Goſpell hath given eſpeciall and expreſſe commands for Subjection, and Reverence to Magiſtrates; yea, though fouly polluted with vices, with tyranny and impieties; as, that ſuch were thoſe, of whom our Saviour and his Apoſtles ſpake, cannot be denied. Therefore no conſequence of a generall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ought to be wreſted, againſt the expreſſe and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Command of honouring the Magiſtrates: leaſt we make the divine will changeable, or repugnant to it's ſelfe; which to ſay were horrible wickednes and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and to beleive it a grand impiety &amp; hereſie. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. by an unheard of example preſumed to attempt this, <hi>Paraeus</hi> has trod in <hi>Hildebrands</hi> ſteps and hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyd that to the Paſtors of the reformed Church; which was moſt vile in the Pontifician Kingdome; which an <hi>Ambroſe</hi> would never have done, nor any holy and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Biſhop in the Church of Chriſt hath ever done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The firſt Propoſition proved by exemples.</note> 
                     <hi>By the Examples of the Prophets, of</hi> Elijah, <hi>who in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39316:12"/>Word reſiſted wicked</hi> Ahab; Jeremiah, <hi>wicked</hi> Joachim; John Baptiſt, <hi>wicked</hi> Herod; <hi>and</hi> Ambroſe, Theodoſius; <hi>for unjuſt ſlaughter, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples cleared.</note> 
                     <hi>Elijah</hi> did recall the King from his errour, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the People in the Truth, both by Word and Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; he ſhut not out the King from the Company of his People for his impiety, he withdrew not the People from their Subjection to the King, he delivered him not as contumacious unto Satan; he commanded not <hi>Obadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> that good man, nor any other to refraine Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with that wicked King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jeremiah</hi> reproved the impious King; I neither read, nor beleive, that in Word he reſiſted the King; of whoſe Peaceable Doctrine, and no way ſeditious Life, <hi>Calvin</hi> ſpeaks in theſe words, <q>
                        <hi>Jeremiah</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth not onely command the Jews to bear patiently the puniſhment inflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon them; but will have them to be ſubject to</hi> Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar; <hi>and not onely forbids them to be ſeditious, but will have them to be ſo Obedient from their Hearts, that God may be witneſſe of their free ſubjection and obedience,</hi> theſe are the Words upon the 29. of <hi>Ieremy verſe</hi> 7.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> the Adulterer, at the requeſt of the Damoſell Dancing before him, beheaded <hi>Iohn:</hi> The Innocency of the Prophet, or the cruelty of the Tyrant, was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to Chriſt; yet did He not revenge the Prophet by force of Arms, He did not deprive the Perſecutors of His Kingdom, He did not deliver him unto Satan, He did not animate the People againſt the Tyrant; being an example unto us, that we ſtrive not againſt perverſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39316:13"/>Kings and ſuch as are wickedly opinioned concerning God</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did not reſiſt <hi>Theodoſius</hi> with threatning Words, but Exhorted Him with calme Language: <hi>I Councell</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I entreat, I beſeech, I admoniſh, I have no cauſe of contumacy againſt thee, but of fear, I dare not offer, if thou be preſent.</hi> This <hi>Ambroſe</hi> tels us concerning this his Act, <hi>In Epiſt.</hi> 28. They who Interpret this fact of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> to be Excommunication (as Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is taken for the Act of exteriour Power, and ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Juriſdiction) they do much wrong to the Truth of the Hiſtory. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had not (ſuch as the Puritans Dreame of) a Presbytery erected as Chriſts Tribunall, from whoſe Government, who ſo exempts even Kings, ſhall be accounted guilty of high Treaſon againſt the Majeſty of Chriſt, as <hi>Beza</hi> Writes, <hi>De Presbyter. &amp; Excommun. p.</hi> 116. <hi>Nortons Edition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did not decree his Letters of Summons againſt <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> neither did he ſend a Meſſenger to cite him being abſent, or accuſe him of Contumacy being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and judicially condemne him. Neither did he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree him to be Excommunicated, not ſentence him Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, nor exclude him (out of the holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and Divine ſolemnities) from the company of the Faithfull. I will diſpatch the whole matter in a few words;<note place="margin">The true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Ambroſe his Act concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſites.</note> The Biſhop with-held the Emperour from the Sacred Myſteries, by no Act of Juriſdiction, but by intermitting his publique Miniſtry, and Sacerdotall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; who would neither performe Divine Service, nor Adminiſter the Holy Sacrament, ſo long as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was preſent; which every Paſtor though no Biſhop might lawfully have done, if he had happened upon an impenitent ſinner, or ſuch an one as did trample upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39316:13"/>thoſe Sacred Myſteries with manifeſt contempt; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Doctrine of the ancient Church, as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> witneſſeth in <hi>Matth. Hom.</hi> 83. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the opinion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Bilſon</hi> (the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of our Age) doth witneſſe in his anſwer to <hi>Cardinall Alanus, part.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 366.</p>
                  <p>But in this Act, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> that good Biſhop did not do well, whoſe default many have endeavoured to excuſe, no man could approve; or can indeed any godly or Juſt eſtimator of the truth. He cauſed the good Emperor (pious, faithfull, penitent, acknowledging his offence publickly, and deprecating the ſame earneſtly) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain from the communion of Prayers, hearing of the Word, and participation of the Sacrament; which Chriſt himſelf would not have done, who admitted <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> to the holy Aſſembly (of his Apoſtles) and hath commanded us to forgive our Brother as often as he ſhall repent.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>The ſecond Propoſition.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Subjects, not private, but conſtituted in the inferiour Magiſtracy; may lawfully, even with Arms, defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Common-wealth, and the Church, or true Religion, againſt the ſuperiour Magiſtrate. Theſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being ſuppoſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The ſecond Propoſition of <hi>Paraeus</hi> confuted,</note> The inferiour Magiſtrate in a Kingdome, has no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but from the King and under the King; which if he abuſe againſt the King or Common-wealth, he is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39316:14"/>deprived at the pleaſure of the King, and ſuffers puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ill miniſtration of his Office; not on the contrary. This power of the Inferiour over his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, is not eſtabliſhed by God, but is introduced by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velliſh malice, or Humane preſumption, againſt the Divine Ordinance, contrary to the Order of Nature, and equity of Law. <hi>Paraeus</hi> ſaw the harſhneſſe of this Propoſition, and therefore hath mollified it with ſome Moderating Conditions.</p>
               </sp>
               <div n="1" type="condition">
                  <head>The firſt Moderating Condition.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When the Superiour Magiſtrate doth degenerate and become a Tyrant.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>This is not to provide a remedy againſt evill Kings, but to help forwards and add to the publique calamity; and indeed to deceive the Reader: <hi>When he Degenerates</hi> (you ſay) <hi>into Tyranny.</hi> But tell me <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> ſeriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly (ſeeing what is Sacred ought not to be eluded) how and when doth he degenerate? he which is a Tyrant in your Judgement, may perchance be a King in mine; and whom you ſuppoſe to be a very good Prince, I may juſtly conceive a very Cruell Tyrant. In this variety therefore of Opinions, the queſtion will be, Whether hath he degenerated? you affirme: I deny: Therefore the Accuſer is to be brought forth, the guilty Arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Witneſſes Produced, and this before a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39316:14"/>Judge,<note place="margin">There is none on Earth under God, that can be a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Judge ouer Princes.</note> ſuch as indeed there is not any on Earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God; which, Scripture teacheth, the Church belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, Reaſon perſwadeth, and the Publique Safety re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
                     <p>The Scripture teacheth: <hi>The King doth whatſoever Pleaſeth Him; Where the Word of a King is, there is Power, and who may ſay unto him, what doſt thou,</hi> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes, 8. verſ. 3.4.</p>
                     <p>The Church beleiveth, <hi>No Man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cyrill</hi>) <hi>doth vilifie the Laws of Kings unpuniſhed; ſaving Kings themſelves, in whom the Crime of prevarication has no place; for it is wiſely ſaid, That he is wicked, that ſaith unto the King, thou doſt unjuſtly,</hi> in Joan. l. 12. c. 56. Theſe are his Words, according with the ſenſe of the Scriptures, and the unanimous conſent of the Church; for as God is the Supreame Head of all, who Judgeth all and is judged by none; So Kings, Princes of the World who Correct and Judge others, may be Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or Judged by none, but by Him only, to whoſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alone they are Subject. Which King <hi>David</hi> had an eye to; who when he was an Adulterer and Murderer, pray'd for the Divine Mercy, ſaying, <hi>Againſt thee onely have I ſinned;</hi> For I acknowledge none other my Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour on Earth ſave thee alone, beſides thee I have no Judge, who may or can compell me to Tryall, Sentence, or Puniſhment for my wickedneſſe. Whence is that of the Poet.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The People to their Soveraign's Scepter brings</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Their awfull reverence, and to</hi> Jove, <hi>their Kings.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reaſon Perſwadeth,</hi> The King is Head of the Body Politique, the Members neither ought to Judge the Head, becauſe they are below it; neither may they cut
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39316:15"/>it off, becauſe thereby they even ceaſe to be Members.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The publique ſafety requireth,</hi> The King being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, will not yeeld to the Conſpirators, although their ſtrength exceed his an hundred fold; He will call to all the Kings about him for help, He will ſeek to His Friends, Allies, Confederates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he will Muſter His Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conary Souldiers, and will in Fury Vindicate the injury that is offered him with Fire and Sword, and (which is often found true by direfull experiments) His Kingdome being loſt, the ruine of the Common-wealth is to Him a miſerable Comfort, and ſad rejoycing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Evill Princes ſeldom remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, with benefit to the Common-wealth.</note>Grant (which yet is not to be granted) that a Tyrant may be reduced into Order, or ejected out of His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by the Inferiour Magiſtrate; yet is He neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced nor ejected, without great dammage to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Death of <hi>Caeſar</hi> brought no remedy to the Romans, but a greater miſchiefe. <hi>Nero</hi> periſhed, but with no good ſucceſſe; The next Year which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after His Death, felt a greater meaſure of calamity, and abundance of bloodſhed, than the nine years which He reigned with Tyranny. The <hi>Athenians</hi> drove out one Tyrant, and brought in Thirty: <hi>Rome</hi> by renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Kings, did not take away Tyranny, but chang'd it. That of the Countryman is old, <hi>Antigonum effodio, I Dig up</hi> Antigonus, when an ill Lord was ſucceeded by a worſe. And who is it that knows not the Fable of the Ulcerous Man? When the Paſſenger would have dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Leeches from off his ſores, it is ſaid he cryed out, Suffer, oh ſuffer them to be: theſe being full ſuck leſſe, but being ſtruck off others will come on, which feed more hungerly, and bite more ſharply. Hiſtories do relate, That many Tyrants have been expold, many
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39316:15"/>ſlain, but ſeldome with benefit to the Common-wealth.<note place="margin">The ſlaying of a Tyrant cannot be with a good Conſcience.</note> Grant it, that the ſlaying of a Tyrant is for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good; yet can it not ſtand with a Good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, becauſe it is forbidden by God.</p>
                     <p>In a Tyrant three Powers concur; of a Father, of an Husband, and of a Maſter. The Sons cannot baniſh their Father; the Wives may not deſert their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; nor the Servants chaſtiſe their Maſters; much leſſe may the Subjects deprive their King of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But be it ſo, that they may, if he degenerates into a Tyrant; ſince there are many kinds of Tyrannies, ſhall they all have the like reaſon of condemning the King? where the puniſhment is not proportioned to the fault, it is unjuſt, and the fore-runner of a greater Tyranny.</p>
                     <p>You cannot be ignorant <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> that there is a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold diſtinction of Tyranny: one doth rage againſt the humane Laws for a private Benefit, with a publique miſchiefe: another doth violate the Divine Law, to the diſhonour of the Creator: A third doth trample upon both Humane and Divine Laws, contrary to all Juſtice and Piety. I confidently aver, That all Tyranny, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it offer Violence to God or Man, ought to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and may not be abrogated, but by him, <hi>who alone doth unlooſe the Bond of Kings, and girdeth their Loines with a Girdle,</hi> Job. 12.18. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſinned moſt wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by Polygamy and Idolatry, without the diminution of His Majeſty, or amiſſion of his Kingdome; <hi>Ahab</hi> Tyrannouſly murdered <hi>Naboth,</hi> perſecuted the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets with Exile and Death; he baniſhed <hi>Gods true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and by his Authority eſtabliſhed <hi>Baals falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> whom neither the Inſeriour Magiſtrate, nor conſent of the People preſumed to repreſſe for his Tyranny. I
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39316:16"/>confeſſe <hi>Jehu</hi> did it, by a Power Extraordinary given to him from Heaven, not committed to him from the Laws. What then could not be done without the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Oracle; at this Day cannot be done, without the contempt of the Divine Deity, contumely to the Sacred Majeſty, and miſchief to the Common-wealth. Hence is that of <hi rend="margQuotes">Peter Martyr, God Armed one only <hi>Jehu</hi> againſt his Lord, which as it was peculiar, ſo is it not to be drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to example:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Note.</note> And after a few words, he tels us, <q>
                           <hi>That cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if it be lawfull to caſt out of their Kingdomes thoſe who rule wickedly; no Princes or Kings will any where be ſafe; for although they govern juſtly and piouſly, yet can they not alway ſatisfie the People.</hi> loc. com. Claſ. 4. c. 20.</q> p-965. Neither doth this moderating condition ſwerve more from true Divinity, then from Civill Policy; as <hi>Bodine</hi> hath obſerved, <q>
                           <hi>de Repub. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>If the Prince be abſolutely ſupreame, as are the true Monarchs of</hi> France, Spaine, England, Scotland, Æthiopia, Turcia, Perſia, Muſcovia, <hi>whoſe Power is not doubtfully queſtioned, nor their high Soveraignty with any of their Subjects divided; in this caſe it is no waies lawfull for any one in particular, or for all in generall, to attempt any thing</hi> de facto, <hi>or by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Law, againſt the Honour and Life of the Prince of Monarch, although he hath committed all the kinds of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes and cruelties which tongue can name. For as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Order of Law, the Subjects have no juriſdiction over the Prince, on whom depends all the power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Commanding; and who not only can recall, from the Magiſtrates, all the power of Judicature committed to them, but alſo he being preſent, the power and juriſdiction of all Magiſtrates, Corporations, Colledges, Orders, and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties doth ceaſe; as we had ſaid before, and ſhall ſpeak more fully afterwards:</hi> Thus Bodine.</q>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="condition">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39316:16"/>
                  <head>The Second Moderating Condition.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When he will inforce them, or others of his Subjects to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Idolatry, or Blaſphemy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>Chriſt, he lived under the Empire of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> the Principality of <hi>Herod,</hi> and Praeſidency of <hi>Pilate.</hi> The Apoſtles flouriſhed under <hi>Caligula, Claudius, Nero, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian.</hi> All Chriſtians lived under Perſecutors, for the the ſpace of three hundred Years. <hi>Hiberius, Hoſius, Athanaſius, Nazianzen, Hilary, Ambroſe, Chryſoſtome, Auguſtine, Hierome,</hi> and many others watered the Church of God with their holy Life, and ſound Doctrine, above a thouſand Years from the Birth of Chriſt; of whom not one hath once opened this Myſtery. But I will nor conteſt with your <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> from their negative au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Chriſt ſubmitted himſelfe in all things (not forbidden by the Divine Law) to <hi>Tiberius, Herod, Pilate;</hi> He himſelfe performed all the duties of Subjection, and gave command that all Chriſtians ſhould performe the like. The Apoſtles declined neither to the right hand nor to the left, from the Doctrine of Chriſt. <hi>The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians which were at Jeruſalem when</hi> James <hi>ſuffered Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, were more in number, and greater in Power than were the Perſecutors of the Apoſtles; But through the fear and reverence they had of God, they ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſlain by a few, rather then that they would ſlay
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39316:17"/>any:</hi> as that Roman <hi>Clement</hi> relates it, <hi>recognition, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>f.</hi> 9. <hi>With the Sect of Chriſtians</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) <hi>it is lawfull to be ſlain it is not lawfull to ſlay,</hi> in Apolog. <hi>None of us</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cyprian</hi>) <hi>when he is apprehended, reſiſteth; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our number be the greater,</hi> ad Demetrianum. <hi>The Souldiers under</hi> Julian <hi>the Apoſtate</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>did diſtinguiſh the Lord Eternall from the Lord Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; and yet for the Lord Eternall, they were ſubject alſo to the Lord Temporall,</hi> Upon Pſ. 124.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Becauſe I fear God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great) <hi>I fear to intermeddle in the Death of the Lombards,</hi> In Epiſt. ad Sabinianum. As for mine own particular <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> If Kings ſhall draw Men on to Idolatry, I had rather imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Saints in their obſervancy, than you in your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency; and that I ſhould chuſe this rather, the Divine Law doth admoniſh and incite.</p>
                     <p>A Law is extant againſt thoſe who ſhall ſeduce, and draw aſide to Idolatry and Blaſphemy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. <hi>If thy Brother the Son of thy Mother, or thy Son, or thy Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the Wife of thy boſome, or thy Friend, which is as thine own Soule, entice thee ſecretly; ſaying, Let us go and ſerve other goods, &amp;c.</hi> The Law is expreſſe concerning a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Son, a Daughter, a Wife, a Friend; but as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Father, in Husband, a Maſter, there is not a Word in the Law. The Law therefore extends not it ſelfe to them therefore the Son is not bound to appeach his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor the Wife her Husband, nor the Servant his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſecretly inticing, or forcibly compelling him to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and although the appeachment of Father, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or Maſter is not expreſly forbidden; yet becauſe God gave an abſolute and perfect Law, to which nothing may be added, and from which nothing may be detracted;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39316:17"/>that is underſtood to be forbidden, which is not expreſt; but eſpecially becauſe, <hi>Penall Laws are to be reſtrained,</hi> as <hi>Toſtatus</hi> hath it upon <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. <hi>q.</hi> 3. That which is not lawfull to do, or at leaſt, which God requires not to be done againſt a Father, an Husband, or Maſter, we may by no means do againſt the King, who (as is before ſaid) is the Father of His Country, the Husband of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and the ſupreame Lord of all His Subjects.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, this Condition is repugnant to the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call precepts; for if they be Bleſſed,<note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                        <hi>who do ſuffer Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for Righteouſneſſe ſake;</hi> then are they not Bleſſed, who will not ſuffer Perſecution for Righteouſneſſe ſake; becauſe, in that they doe nor ſuffer, but riſe up againſt their Perſecutors, they are convinced of ſinne, and by ſinning get to themſelves Damnation.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="condition">
                  <head>The Third Moderating Condition.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When ſome horrible injury is offered them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>Chriſt himſelfe ſuffered <hi>horrible injury,</hi> which <hi>Peter</hi> willing to Vindicate, he was repreſſed by our Lord. The Perſecutors in the times of the Primitive Church, did afflict the Chriſtians with <hi>horrible injuries,</hi> and under <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperor, the Catholique Faith, did ſuffer the moſt Horrible of Injuries, which in the former and purer age of the Church did not ſo much as think of Revenge. <hi>Baronius</hi> himſelfe will witneſſe it,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39316:18"/>who writing about the Yeare 350. ſaith,<note place="margin">When Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians firſt began to be Antimonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians.</note> 
                        <hi>Hee firſt the Chriſtians Captain enraged, with a curſed deſire of reigning, conſpired againſt the Chriſtian Emperors, whereas in times paſt, not ſo much as a Common ſouldier could be found, who ſided with the rebelling tyrants againſt the Emperors, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were Heathens and Perſecutors of Chriſtians:</hi> From Chriſt, thoſe Chriſtians, and true Catholiks, did the Faithfull learn their patience under the Turkiſh cruelty, and the Proteſtants under the Popiſh Tyranny: which I think <hi>(Pareus)</hi> I will ſpeak freely.<note place="margin">The evils which follow upon the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> You do <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible injury</hi> to Chriſt himſelf, all good Chriſtians; yea, even to mankinde, by this your Doctrine; which now ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth throughout the Chriſtian World, to the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Citizens, ſlaughters of Princes, and proſcriptions of Kings, to the ruine of the Faith, and almoſt utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Chriſtianity it ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Paraeus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by King <hi>James,</hi> the Biſhop of London and his Clergy, and by the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of Oxford.</note>From whence it was, that the moſt Soveraign King, Head (under Chriſt) of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the true Defendor of the Catholique Faith, and aſſertor of the Chriſtian Truth, purged your Commentaries with ſire: The Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> (a Man greater than praiſe can make him, born to the good of the Church, of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and of Learning it ſelfe) together with his whole Clergy, condemned this your fourth queſtion, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Civill Power of Hereſie and Sedition. Your foure Propoſitions, brought to ſtrict Examination, the Univerſitie of <hi>Oxford</hi> did not weigh in a Popular Scale, but corrected them by the Gold-Smiths Ballance; and that by a Publike Decree of the whole Univerſitie.</p>
                     <p>Why might not our Soveraign King commit to the revenging Flames? why might not the <hi>Orthodox Biſhop</hi> paſſe ſentence and condemne? why might not the <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demian
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39316:18"/>Muſes</hi> altogether baniſh? what Chriſt, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Fathers, Schoolemen, Proteſtants, and more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Papiſts have all, at all times, in all places utterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. Of ſo great an heap, I will give you a ſmall hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Antimonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt</note>Chriſt. <hi>I ſay unto you, that ye reſiſt not evill, but whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall ſmite thee on the one Cheeke, turn to him the other alſo,</hi> Math. 5.39.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Apoſtles.</note>
                        <q>Peter. <hi>This is thankworthy, if a Man for Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God endure griefe ſuffering wrongfully; for what glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is it, if when you be buffeted for your faults you take it patiently? but if when ye do well and ſuffer for it ye take it patiently, this is acceptable with God,</hi> 1 Pet. c. 2. v. 19.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ancient Fathers.</note> 
                        <q>Tertullian. <hi>One Night could worke our revenge abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly with a few fire-brands, were it a thing lawfull with us to render evill for evill, far be it that the Divine Sect ſhould either ſeek revenge by humane fire, or grieve to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that whereby it is approved. So he in his Apology.</hi> Tell me <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> how could <hi>Tertullian</hi> live under the Sword of Perſecutors without <hi>horrible injury?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Nazianzen. <hi>Julian was repreſſed by the Tears of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which many abundantly ſhed, having that onely reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt the Perſecutors,</hi> in Julian. orat. 1. They had other remedy (<hi>Paraeus</hi> being Judge) If <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, the vileſt of Emperours, had offered ſome <hi>hainous injury</hi> to the Chriſtians.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Ambroſe. <hi>It was required of me that I ſhould appeaſe the People: I anſwered, It was my part and Duty not to ſtir them up; it was in the hand of God to appeaſe them.</hi> Epiſt. 33. It had been here your part <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> to have ſtirted up a Popular Revenge for the <hi>hainous injury</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperor.</q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:39316:19"/>
                     <p>Proſper of Aquitania. <hi>Let preſent evils be endured, till the promiſed bliſſe be obtained; let the unfaithfull be born with by the faithfull, and the plucking up the Tares differed; although the wicked rage, yet is the cauſe of the juſt even in this time the better; who, by how much they are aſſaulted the more fiercely, by ſo much they are Crowned the more gloriouſly,</hi> Sent. 99. Declare to us <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> what ſhall be the violence of the wicked againſt the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, without <hi>horrible injury?</hi> my dulneſſe cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it.</p>
                     <p>Bernard. <hi>If all the World ſhould conſpire againſt me, to force me to attempt any thing againſt the Royall Majeſty, yet would I fear God, and not dare raſhly to offend the King ordain'd by him, for I am not ignorant how I have Read, he that reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the ordinance of God,</hi> Epiſt. 170. to King <hi>Lewis.</hi> Dareſt thou not <hi>(Bernard)</hi> to remove the <hi>horrible injury,</hi> offered even to the whole Clergy? all whoſe goods King <hi>Lewis</hi> had invaded; and which was worſe, he would heare no admonitions for Amendment or Reſtitution, as <hi>Robert Gaguinus</hi> hath it, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. without doubt either <hi>Bernard</hi> err'd, or <hi>Paraeus</hi> dotes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">School-men.</note> Let us turn aſide (if you pleaſe) into the Schooles, where preſently will meet us our Countryman, <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der de Hales,</hi> who concerning the Duty of Subjects to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Princes, has theſe words: <hi>The evill ought to be ſubject for the fault of their unreaſonableneſſe; but the good f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r that Duty they owe to the Divine Ordinance, and the benefit of purging themſelves.</hi> From whence <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon that, <hi>Princes are not a terrour, &amp;c. If the Prince be good, he doth not puniſh, but love him that doth well; but if he be evill, he doth not hurt, but purge: he is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39316:19"/>a terrour to him that doth well: But the wicked ought to fear, becauſe Princes are appointed to puniſh the wicked.</hi> Thus he, part. 3. queſt. 48. memb. 2. art. 1. Doſt thou heare <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> the Power of the Superiour, though cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and unjuſt, doth not hurt, but purge the Righteous.</p>
                     <p>Will you heare <hi>Aquinas? The Faith of Chriſt is the beginning and cauſe of Righteouſneſſe, and therefore by the Faith of Chriſt, the order of Juſtice is not abrogated, but confirmed: and the order of Juſtice requires, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours obey the Superiours, otherwiſe the ſtate of humane affairs cannot be preſerved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore the Faithfull, by the Faith of Chriſt are not excuſed from their obedience to ſecular Princes,</hi> in 2.2. q. 104. art. 6. Have you it now <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> Faith doth not ſubject the Superiours to the Inferiours againſt the Order of Juſtice; neither doth it permit the Power of the Sword to the Subject againſt the Prince upon any cauſe, becauſe that inordinate Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would tend to the deſtruction of all humane things.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">See the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth reaſon from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Proteſtant Divines.</note>The Faithfull Flock of Chriſt, long ſince, and at this Day obey the Turk, not without <hi>horrible injury,</hi> yet are they Subject, and alwaies have been, not for wrath, but for Conſcience ſake; and amongſt the Proteſtants, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Melancthon, Brentius, Cranmer</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, Tyndall,</hi> and <hi>Barnes</hi> doe condemne this error with an Anathema. To whom I add the famous Example of a brave Prince; an Example acceptable to God, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for the Common-wealth, honourable to the Prince: which I would have thee Reade (<hi>Paraeus,</hi> that thou mayſt learn to be wiſe) in<note n="*" place="margin">Berchet, in explicat. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſiae Gal licanae. c. <hi>7.</hi> Servinus pro libertate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, &amp; Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Regni. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchiae Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae. p. <hi>202.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Berchetus,</hi> and <hi>Johannes Servinus:</hi> I will relate it in briefe, <hi>When in France</hi> (after the Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre in Paris) <hi>the reformed Religion ſeem'd as it were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and almoſt extinct</hi> (which I thinke could not be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39316:20"/>
                        <hi rend="margQuotes">done without <hi>horrible injury: A certain King, powerfull in ſtrength, rich in Gold, and dreadfull in his Navy; with whom when the King of</hi> France <hi>was at odds, he diſpacht a ſolemne Embaſſage to</hi> Henry <hi>King of</hi> Navarre, <hi>and other</hi> Proteſtants <hi>it was commanded the Embaſſadors, that they ſhould ſet the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>and</hi> Papiſts <hi>at ſtrife together, and to Arme Prince</hi> Henry (who lived at Bearne under the Government of the Chriſtian King) <hi>againſt the King; which they endeavoured with all Art and cunning attempt,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                           <hi>but in vain.</hi> Henry <hi>a good Subject, and as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> David, <hi>being himſelf to be King, he would not fore-run the Day of the Lord. The Embaſſadors offered large, rich, and bountifull Conditions, amongſt the reſt there was ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd three hundred thouſand Crowns in readineſſe to make preparation of War, and a neceſſary ſumme for continuing the War was to be payd every Moneth.</hi> Henry <hi>a faithfull Chriſtian, a good Prince, de prived of his Wife, removed from the publique Adminiſtration of the Common-wealth, and for whoſe ſake, the King had baniſht very many</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,, <hi>and ſlain their</hi> Paſtors (I would have you <hi>Paraeus</hi> to acknowledge the words of your own <hi>Bucan</hi>) <hi>yet did not</hi> Henry <hi>ſtretch out his hand againſt the Lords Annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; he would have none of their Gold, he refuſed the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and diſmiſt the Embaſſadors; as Witneſſe of his Faith towards God, his faithfulneſſe towards his King, and his peaceable mind towards his Country.</hi>
                        </hi> There remains now no ſtarting hole for you <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> here was an <hi>horrible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury</hi> done to the Inferiour Magiſtrate as well as others, yet becauſe a Lawfull Power was wanting to <hi>Henry</hi> (which you Dream to be ordinary) againſt the Power ordained by God; he choſe rather according to Chriſts precept, to ſuffer a Greivous Injury with patience,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39316:20"/>than according to your Preſcript, to reſiſt the Power ordained by God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">What hath been the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the Proteſtants.</note>This is <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> and ever has been the Religion of the Proteſtants, not to offer but to ſuffer injuries; to render good for evill, and not to repreſſe Perſecutors placed in Authority by Force or Sword, but procure their favour by Patience, Love, and Benevolence; which truth, even the more moderate Papiſts themſelves do not abhorre, who are averſe from the Tyranny of the Papall Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and the popular Anarchy of the Puritans. <hi>William Barclay</hi> may be one in ſtead of all, his Words are theſe: <hi>Oftentimes there happens cauſes, for which we are not bound to doe the commands of the Magiſtrate,</hi> namely; <hi>when he commands contrary to the commands of God. But there can be no cauſe why we ſhould reſiſt him, executing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſentence of condemnation,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                        <hi>and requiring puniſhment out of malice, under pretence of Authority, becauſe he has power ordained him by God, which if he abuſeth, he is to be reſtrained by lawfull means, not by the violence of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> and after a few Lines, <hi>Nothing remains to the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but that he commit his cauſe to the knowledge of the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent God, and that he expect his Judgement who is King of Kings, and the Judge of all Judges, he will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly chaſtice and correct the injuſtice of the ſentence by the ſeverity of his eternall Juſtice:</hi> Thus he, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 10. Remember <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> this your <hi>horrible injury,</hi> and repent.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="condition">
                  <head>The Fourth Moderating Condition.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If they cannot otherwiſe be ſafe in their Fortunes, Lives, and Conſciences.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:39316:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>O the Blindneſſe of the Primitive Church, of the Ancient Fathers! to whom that light of a New Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel hath not ſhined. Thoſe men born to miſery (or this Divinity is falſe) have altogether erred, who were ſo willing patiently to undergoe the pangs of Martyrdom, and when they were both the more in number, and the ſtronger in power, would not by Force and Arms de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Fortunes from the Tyrants, their Lives from the Perſecutors, or their Faith from Hereticall Kings.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="condition">
                  <head>The firſt Moderating Condition.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That under pretence of Religion or Juſtice, they ſeek not their own.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Juſtice and Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>igi on the pretence of Rebellion.</note>A Subject (of what condition ſoever he be) who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the King, ſeeks not his own, but covers other Mens Goods, yet obtains them not, unleſſe he pretend juſtice and Religion. <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf doth not deceive Men, but as transformed into an Angell of Light; neither doth Vice deceive any Man, unleſſe it aſſume the name of Honeſty.</p>
                     <p>What need of pretence <hi>Paraeus?</hi> Rebellion it ſelf is Juſtice and Religion; and by how much any is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in Treachery and Treaſon, by ſo much is he accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the more Juſt and Holy. I would to God this our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39316:21"/>Age were not an eye-witneſſe of this Religious Juſtice. Let an inferiour Magiſtrate inforce his Superiour into Order, though to the diminution of Majeſty. <hi>Buchanan</hi> (a Man, if we give any credit to the Conſiſtorians,<note place="margin">
                           <p>T. B.</p> 
                           <p>L. D.</p>
                        </note> moſt excellent and the light of his Age) he will cry out proſently, <hi>an Act juſt, holy, and prayſe worthy,</hi> and that not in one place alone, but almoſt in every page of foure Books, which he compoſed to the envie of one Prince, and the injury of all Kings.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Traytors magnified by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</note>Let <hi>Parry</hi> draw his Dagger; he ſhall forthwith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Apoſtolicall Benediction, for the Remiſſion of his ſins, and Salvation of his Soule. Let a Monke ſtab a King, he ſhall be extold in the prayſes of ſlaying <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernes,</hi> even this in the Conſiſtory of the Pope.</p>
                     <p>Let a Traytor attempt the Deſtruction of King and Kingdom by Gunpowder, he ſhall be inſerted into the Catalogue of Martyrs. Let <hi>Caſtellus</hi> ſtrik at the throat of a King, or break his tooth, he ſhall be honoured to eternity under the name of <hi>Franciſcus Veronenſis Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus,</hi> in the Elogy of <hi>John Boucher;</hi> heare ye Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike men what the Father the Jeſuite thinks of thoſe holy men and Religious. <hi>If they eſcape death, they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired as great Worthies; if it happen otherwiſe: they fall by their noble endeavours, a Sacrifice acceptable to the Gods, acceptable to men, even to the Memory of all poſterity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">By the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians.</note> Heare alſo a noble payre of Puritan Brothers, <hi>Were it lawfull for me to make a Law; I would command rewards to be appointed to the ſlayers of Tyrants, not onely by all the People, but by each of them: as it is commonly wont to be done to them, who have ſlain Wolves or Bears, or caught any of their Whelps,</hi> Buchan, de Jure Regni, p. 31. <hi>All Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens which are lovers of their Country, and which deſire the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39316:22"/>ſafety of the Commonwealth, ought to adjoyne themſelves to the inferiour Magiſtrate, againſt the Supreame; and thoſe ſame men (Victory being gotten) are to be preferred before the reſt, in obtaining the dignities of the Kingdom, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them eſpecially who gave back, and adjoyned not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him.</hi> Thus <hi>Danaeus</hi> de politia Chriſtiana, lib. 6. pag. 460.</p>
                     <p>Who doth not abhorre this monſtrous kind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines? in diſproving whereof, he doth but miſuſe his pains, who abounds with leiſure and Learning. Let paſſe this pretence <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> it is not lawfull for the Subject to reſiſt the King,<note place="margin">We may not reſiſt the King upon any pretence of Religion or Juſtice.</note> though a Tyrant, upon any cauſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; either of true Religion, or of Juſtice, without inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Divine Law, the Goſpell of Chriſt, and Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ancient Church. <hi>Moſes</hi> had the true cauſe of Juſtice, who revenged his Brother upon the Ægypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. <hi>Peter</hi> had a true zeal of Religion, when he would have delivered his moſt innocent Lord, oppreſſed with moſt <hi>horrible injury,</hi> from the hands of his Perſecutors. Yet did <hi>Moſes</hi> offend, and ſo did <hi>Peter;</hi> both (that I may uſe the words of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) did exceed the rule of Juſtice: he (that is <hi>Moſes</hi>) offended, through the love he had to his Brother; and the other (that is <hi>Peter</hi>) through the love he had to his Maſter: againſt <hi>Fauſtus Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus, l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 70.</p>
                     <p>That which was not lawfull, long ſince, for <hi>Moſes</hi> in the behalfe of his Brother; that which was not lawfull for <hi>Peter,</hi> in the behalfe of his Maſter, and the Religion of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is not at this day lawfull for any man, for Religions ſake, whether it be Roman or Reformed; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be by a New Goſpel, not yet fully reveal'd to the Chriſtian World. That Decree of the ancient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39316:22"/>held at <hi>Eliboris,</hi> is well known. If any ſhall<note n="*" place="margin">That is, without law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> break in pieces the Idols, and there (or then) be ſlain; becauſe it is not found commanded in the Goſpel, or practiſed by the Apoſtles, it hath pleaſed us (to decree) that he be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the number of Martyrs, <hi>Can.</hi> 60. Yea, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and purer Church hath deteſted this Juſtice and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, more than either Dog or Serpent, of whoſe praiſe Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks <hi>De Civit. Dei, l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>The City of Chriſt, though it was a ſtranger on Earth, and had great troops of people againſt the wicked perſecutors, yet did it not fight for temporall ſafety; but rather not reſiſt, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain eternall ſafety.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">To take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant were it lawfull, yet is it not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.</note>True Religion was alwaies humble, and the conſerver of Kingdoms. The falſe Religion, that hath alwaies ſet Kings at odds, and Arm'd the Subjects againſt their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours; from whence it appears, this is not the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; but ſuch as hath put on the faire ſhew and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous maske of Piety; and the better the Author is of which it boaſteth; the more deteſtable it is.</p>
                     <p>I will ſay further; were it a thing Lawfull, yet were it not a thing expedient: For the miſerable People whilſt they endeavour to ſhun the Scylla of one Mans Tyranny; they fall headlong upon that Charybdis of many Tyrannies. All things ſhall be expoſed to deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, and deſtruction: The Peaſant will inſult over the Nobleman; the Servant, over his Maſter; the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, over the Rich; the Oppreſſor, over the Citizen; the Adulterer over the Matron; the Lecher over the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin; the Pyrat over the Merchant; the Thief, over the Traveller; and the Spoyler, over the Husbandman: Laſtly, one Man will be a Wolfe to another. This evill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iberty will endure no Law; no Law will make a moſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39316:23"/>miſerable Common-wealth; when every man may doe what ſeemeth good in his own eyes, as it was in thoſe Dayes, when there was no King in Iſrael.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="condition">
                  <head>The Sixth Moderating Condition.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A favourable Interpretation being alwaies reſerved, and the ordering of an unblameable defence according to the Laws.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>It is not <hi>an unblameable Defence,</hi> but a moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sedition to reſiſt the Superiour. The places of Scripture againſt this Sedition are ſo clear and manifeſt, that they cannot be eluded by any ſly evaſion, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. whoſoever therefore ſhall offer violence (unto any man) not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by an ordinate power, is guilty of ſinning; both againſt the Divine and humane Majeſty. To the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating Conditions, he hath adjoyned ſome Reaſons, whereof the firſt is,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Becauſe the Superiour Magiſtrate is ſubject to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Laws and to his Commonwealth; which appears in</hi> Deut. ch. 17. Joſhua 1.8.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Paraeus his Reaſons an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</note>That the King is ſubject to the Divine Laws, Who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39316:23"/>denyes? he is ſubject alſo to the Laws of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, though not in the ſame manner; to the Divine Laws abſolutely; and to the Laws of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, not for 'its coaction, but direction; as <hi>Thomas</hi> witneſſeth; <hi>The Prince is ſaid to be free from the Laws as concerning the coactive power of the Law; becauſe no Man can paſſe Sentence of Condemnation upon him: but as concerning the directive power of the Law, he is not free,</hi> 1.2. queſt. 96. art. 5. ad. 3.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Law of God, doth not onely forbid Tyranny, but alſo commands it to be lawfully reſtrained. He that ſheds Mans Blood, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">God the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remover of Tyrants.</note>He that is Lord of all forbids Tyranny, and takes it away, when, and how he will; at his command <hi>Jehu</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheaths his Sword; where God commands not, <hi>Peter</hi> puts up his Sword, even in the cauſe of Chriſt. For if any will betake himſelfe to his Arms, without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Superiour, he ſhall preſently heare, <hi>He that ſtriketh with the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword;</hi> For God will not have an evill taken away, but in a lawfull manner, and by lawfull means. Though therefore it be juſt that Tyrants ſhould ſuffer; yet moſt unjuſt that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhould inflict puniſhment. God brought againſt <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Frogs, Flyes, Locuſts, Haile, and other Plagues of that ſort; he did not ſtir up his Subjects againſt him. Againſt the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he armed the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39316:24"/>Forraigne Enemy, not the native Citizen. That place in <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Fevardentius</hi> long ſince wreſted to the ſame ſence, whom <hi>Paraeus</hi> now follows; but with little credit. For God will not that Mans Blood be ſhed, but by a Man Inveſted with Authority: as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes directly againſt <hi>Fauſtus Manichaeus, lib.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 70. but to no Man living is there Power or Juriſdiction gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over the Superiour Magiſtrate, as <hi>O tho Friſingenſis</hi> hath it: <hi>For ſeeing it is a dreadfull thing to all Men, to fall into the hands of the living God, to Kings (who have none above them but God whom they may fear) it is ſo much the more dreadfull, by how much they may ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> with the more freedom,</hi> in Epiſt. ad Freder. Ænobarb.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alſo becauſe the Emperour witneſſeth himſelfe that he would not, that his decrees ſhould have place in judgements againſt Law; but that they become voyd, if by chance they be known to depart from Juſtice, and</hi> lib. 4. cap. de lege Princip. <hi>A voice it is worthy the Majeſty of a King; to profeſſe himſelfe bound to his Laws.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>What? ſhall that which is granted for Publique Peace and Juſtice ſake, be turned to an occaſion of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide? Emperours, they are the Authors, Interpreters, and Defenders of the Laws, to which they freely ſubmit themſelves, but are compelled by none. That which the Clemency of the King doth indulge to the Prelats, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, or Commons, doth neither diminiſh His Majeſty,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39316:24"/>nor confer upon them any Right or Power above the Prince; who ſo deſires more, let him conſult <hi>Barclay</hi> againſt the <hi>Monarchomachi, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. the Apology for Kings, <hi>cap.</hi> 34. <hi>Saravia de imper. author. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp; Joannes Roffenſis, de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpata Pontif. poteſt, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore alſo the Tyranny and Robberies of the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Magiſtrate, ought to be reſtrained by the ordinary Power; which in every Polity, is either the Inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or the conſent of the People.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Princes though wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are not to be reviled.</note> 
                        <hi>Tyranny and Robbery,</hi> are the revilings of Magiſtrates, unbeſeeming a Divine, not ſavouring of the Spirit of the Prophets. There were very many Kings of the Jews, and have been in the Church of Chriſt, who have Reigned Tyrannouſly, Worſhipped Idols, forcibly drawn their Subjects to Idolatry, and afflicted the innocent with <hi>horrible injury;</hi> of whom not one in all the Sacred or Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory, or in the Ancient Fathers, is called by the name of <hi>Tyrant</hi> or <hi>Robber</hi> (if we except but the revilings of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer Calaritanus</hi> againſt <hi>Conſtantius</hi>) that we may learn, that Kings, Gods Vicegerents, though they abuſe that Power, are not to be reviled with a reproachfull Tongue. <hi>The Actions of thoſe who are ſet over us</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great) <hi>are not to be ſtruck at by the Sword of the Mouth, no not even then, when they are judged juſtly to be reproved; but if the Tongue at any time ſlip out againſt them, though
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39316:25"/>but in the ſmalleſt matters, it is neceſſary, that the Heart be afflicted in repentance, that he may return to himſelf; and ſeeing he hath offended the Power ſet over him, he may tremble at the judgement of him, who hath ſet the Power over him,</hi> thus he, <hi>Paſtor. part.</hi> 3. <hi>adm.</hi> 5. <hi>fol.</hi> 16. This Concluſion gathered from falſe Propoſitions, is ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and deſtructive of all Monarchy: For if the chief coercive Power in every Polity be in the Inferiour Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or the conſent of the People, the World will not have in it one Monarch; which let them look to, to whom the Power, the Right, and rule of Government belongs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Becauſe it is the duty of the Inferiour Magiſtrate, no leſſe then of the Superiour, to defend the Life and ſafety of the Subjects againſt the horrible injuries, and unjuſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Robbers and Tyrants, whether Forraign or Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick; which is proved, becauſe of them it is ſaid. He is the Miniſter of God for thy good, He is not a terrour to good Works, but to the bad; He beareth not the Sword in vain, he taketh vengeance on him that doth evill, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Kings not ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the Inferiour Magiſtrate.</note> 
                        <hi>Paraeus</hi> in the Explication of that Text in <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. followed <hi>Fevardentius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> here he is plain <hi>Buchanan,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Sence of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the unanimous conſent of the Church. For the actions of Kings cannot be brought to puniſhment, becauſe they have no Man to be a competent Judge over them: the Inferiour Magiſtrate is Subject to the Superiour, by whom he ſuffers the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39316:25"/>puniſhment due unto his committed wickedneſſe, the Superiour is held guilty before God alone, not before any Mortall Man, as <hi>Toſtatus</hi> moſt truely: <hi>If any of the Rulers over Ten had ſinned, he was brought to his tryall before the Rulers over Fifties; if any of them had ſinned, he was brought to his Triall before the Rulers over Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds; if any of them had ſinned, he was brought to his tryall before the Heads over the tribes; if any of them had ſinned, he was brought to his tryall before the Seventy El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; if any of them had ſinned, he was brought to his tryall before</hi> Moſes; <hi>if</hi> Moſes <hi>had ſinned, He had God alone to be His Avenger.</hi> Thus he, upon <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.9.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alſo, becauſe the Inferiour Magiſtrates are therefore added to the Superiour, both that they may be Companions in their Government, and alſo, that they may moderate their immenſe Liberty; which, therefore, when they do bridle, they uſe the Authority and Sword, delivered unto them by the Divine Power, by a Lawfull calling.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">A great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Parae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</note>Here <hi>Paraeus</hi> is ſhamefully deceived, with hazard to them who are ſo addicted to him, as a tryed Man, for his ſingular Learning; that they think they may ſafely Beleive, whatſoever he Affirms; and Reject whatſoever he Diſallowes. For there is not in the Sacred Scripture any Foot-ſtep of this Authority, which he averts to be delivered by the Divine Power. God the diſpoſer and preſerver of Politicall Order, never inſtituted this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39316:26"/>Power; God (I ſay) not the People deſigned <hi>Moſes, Joſuah,</hi> and the <hi>Judges,</hi> and guirt them with the Sword. <hi>Moſes</hi> Gods Vicar, He numbers the Heads of the Tribes, conſtituted the Seventy Elders, appointed the Tribunes, Centurians, Quinquagenarians, and Decu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; who ever acknowledged themſelve, nor Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to <hi>Moſes</hi> in Government, but his Subjects. And all the reſt of the Kings, alwaies choſe to themſelves Councellors and Inferiour Magiſtrates, both to leſſen their care and carefulnes, and that they might have Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in handling &amp; diſpatching their more difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; not that thoſe Magiſtrates may make any Law to moderate the Royall Liberty, or to revenge their Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; he affirms, but proves not, that the Inferiour Power is added to the Superiour for revenge and wrath. <hi>If it be commanded, it is preſumption, and ſhall procure puniſhment, not reward, becauſe it redounds to the diſgrace of the Creator;</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>that the Servants ſhould be honoured, the Head being deſpiſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that the followers ſhould be reverenced, the Emperour being contemned.</hi> This Addition therefore is point blank againſt the opinion of the Fathers and Proteſtants (of whom we ſhall ſpeak in due place) as alſo the moſt Learned Men, who have in this our Age, illuſtrated the Civill Polity with their writings: conſult <hi>Bodine de Repub. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. the Apology for Kings, <hi>cap.</hi> 27. <hi>Barclay</hi> againſt the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchom. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Berchet in explic. controver. Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Saravia de imper. author. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 36. <hi>Sigonius de Repub. Judaeor. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Note.</note> The Magiſtrates which are above the People, are below the King; whence it is, that neither the People may reſiſt the Magiſtrate, nor the Magiſtrate reſiſt the King, without Sacriledge.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39316:26"/>Chriſt himſelfe hath taught, and ſo the Apoſtles, and the Diſciples of the Apoſtles, and all Interpreters of Divine and Humane Laws have taught us, That <hi>the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neither ought to he judged, nor condemned by the leſſer;</hi> Neither was it ever lawfull for the Pope, Nobility, or People, to chaſtiſe the King, till <hi>Hildebrands</hi> firebrands were kindled, to the ſetting on fire all Chriſtendom. This Doctrine therefore is novell and Inſolent; whereof there is not extant in either the Old or New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, any Precept, or probable Example. If there be any, let it be produced, and I will yeeld my ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, and become ſlave to the Fathers the Jeſuits, and to the Brethren the Puritans. We have this truth clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and confirmed in Writings which ſhall remain, committed to Poſterity, by <hi>Thomas Bilſon</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in the ſeventh Chapter of his Perpetuall Government of the Church, and <hi>Peter Greg. Tholoſ. de Repub. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>num.</hi> 14.15.16.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In whoſe power it is to conſtitute; in their power it is to reſtrain or take away thoſe, who rage in a diſorderly vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: but they are conſtituted, either by the conſent of the People, or by the Senate, or by the Electors, or by other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates; Therefore theſe doe well, when they either reſtrain or take them away.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>This Aſſertion is Capitall, which the Emperour will not admit, the King will not ſuffer; which <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:39316:27"/>himſelfe doth affirme to be rejected by the conſent of all Divines, that it is not neceſſary for me to refute it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Magiſtrate that is mad, is juſtly removed by Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Authority; as</hi> Nebuchadnezzer <hi>being turn'd into a furious Beaſt, was driven out from the Company of Men,</hi> Dan. 4.31.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>The caſting out of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: as there are many things by Divine command in the Sacred Scriptures;<note place="margin">How Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar was driven out is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</note> which without Sacriledge cannot be drawn into example. Howſoever, the manner of his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out, is doubtfull and uncertain, <hi>Calvin</hi> being Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>It is uncertain, whether God ſmote this King with fury, ſo, as that he fled away, and lay hid for ſome time;</hi> (they are the words of <hi>Calvin</hi>) <hi>or that he was caſt out by a Tumult, and Conſpiracy of his Nobles; or elſe by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the whole People. This is doubtfull, becauſe the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of thoſe times are unknown to us;</hi> and that indeed he was not turned into a wilde Beaſt; the ſame <hi>Calvin</hi> will tell us: <hi>It is probable</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he was ſo aſtoniſht, that God left him the Forme of a Man, but took away his reaſon.</hi> This <hi>Calvin</hi> upon <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.32. From a Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lou; Act, and from doubtfull and uncertain Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to gather a ſure and certain rule, is the part of him who hath little Brains in his Head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A raging and cruell Tyrant is like to a mad Man.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:39316:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>All theſe are very ill compared together. Every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Man is Armed by the Divine Law, the inſtinct of Nature, and publique Authority, againſt Robbers and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent ſpoilers: a Tyrant being ſeated in an higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is liable to puniſhment by no Humane Laws, being ſafe in the height of his Empire. Whence it was, that David, <hi>not ignorant of the Divine Ordinance in the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Regall Order, he honoured</hi> Saul (a Tyrant, and defiled with all kinde of wickedneſſe) <hi>as yet placed in that ſame Divine Ordinance, leaſt he might ſeem to do injury to God, who hath decreed honour to thoſe Orders. For the King hath the Image of God, as the Biſhop the Image of Chriſt. So long then, as he is in that Divine Ordinance, he is to be honoured, if not for himſelf, yet for the Orders ſake,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath it,<note place="margin">The Reaſon not the ſame for a tyrant and a mad King.</note> in <hi>queaſt.</hi> out of the Old Teſtament, <hi>qu.</hi> 35. Neither in all things, is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the ſame, for a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and for a <hi>mad Man. Tyranny</hi> doth proceed from Pride, Covetouſneſſe, Cruelty, Wickedneſſe, and innate Malice. <hi>Madneſſe</hi> doth not proceed, but from ill affected Nature; and the Laws do not puniſh Diſſeaſes, but Impieties. A Magiſtrate that is <hi>Mad</hi> (ſaith <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> is juſtly removed; juſtly good Sir? that is juſt, which agrees with the Rule of Juſtice, this oppoſeth all Rule. The Law of Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives no Man of his Right; by the Law of Nations, Kingdoms are not poſſeſt by Vertue, or Wiſdom, but deſcent. The Civill Laws do not permit any defect in the mind, to be any hinderance, whereby Kings may be accounted Legitimate; to whom they preſcribe a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39316:28"/>Protector, an Aſſiſtant, or Miniſter of State to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, leaſt the welfare of the Subjects, and ſafety of the Common-wealth be put to hazard; concerning whom, conſult the Apology for Kings, <hi>cav.</hi> 20. <hi>Barclay contra Monarch. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. and <hi>Saravia de imperandi authorit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 39.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The ſame is confirmed by worthy Examples, both Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Prophane. The</hi> Iſraelites <hi>oftentimes by their Judges made Inſurrection againſt the Neighbouring Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, by whom they were cruelly handled.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>There is nothing that can be produced ſo wicked, ſo abſurd, or ſo fooliſh, whereof an Example may not be drawn out of Sacred and Profane Hiſtory: but theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> prove nothing;<note place="margin">Why the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus prove nothing.</note> becauſe they are all, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlike, or falſe, or onely of Fact, or unjuſt in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: From the Acts of the Judges, by Gods extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary command, he collects that ordinary rule. How falſly, learn of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon Judges, <hi>cap.</hi> 20. This vain Argument is met with alſo, by the Author of that Book, <hi>de Regimine Principum,</hi> which is carried about under the name of <hi>Thomas Aquinas. It hath been thought by ſome</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that it beſeems the valour of couragious Men to ſlay a Tyrant, and to expoſe themſelves to the danger of death for the Liberty of a Multitude; an Example whereof is had in the Old Teſtament; For</hi> Ehud <hi>killed</hi> Eglon; <hi>but this agreeth not with the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39316:28"/>for</hi> Peter <hi>teacheth us to ſubmit with reverence, not onely to good and gracious Maſters, but alſo to the froward; for this is thank worthy, if a Man for Conſcience toward God, endure grief ſuffering patiently; whence it was, that when many Roman Emperours, did tyrannically perſecute the Faith of Chriſt; and a great multitude both of the Nobles, and of the People were converted to the Faith, it was prayſed, not for making reſiſtance, but ſuffering death,</hi> lib. 1. cap. 6.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>Exechias, <hi>the holy King, fell away from the Aſsyrian Tyrant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and when he raiſed War againſt him, he defended himſelf by Arms,</hi> 2 King. 18.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>The King of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſubdued the King of <hi>Aſsyria,</hi> in a juſt War. Therefore it is lawfull for the Inferious Magiſtrate to remove the Prince, who is Supreame, for his impiety, phrenſie, or tyranny, a very peremptory con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, not to be retorted with words, but blows.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It matters not, that theſe were Forraign Tyrants, for domeſtick Tyrants differ nothing from Forraigne; yea, they are the rather to be repreſſed, becauſe they are perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the more hurtfull.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>Shall I beleive <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> that there was no difference
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39316:29"/>(as concerning the debt of duty) between the King of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the Subjects of the King of Aſſyria? not ſo truely, were you <hi>Pythagoras</hi> himſelf. Neither is that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes lawfull, in thoſe things which are more hurtfull; which is lawfull, in thoſe things which are leſſe hurtfull. Seditious Preachers (the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> being Witneſſe) are a Generation of Vipers; yea, peradventure much more hurtfull than Vipers, becauſe Vipers doe but hurt the Body; thoſe Preachers deſtroy both Body and Soule. Therefore as any man may ſlay a venemous Viper; ſo is it lawfull for any Man to ſlay thoſe Tribune-like Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: A conſequence that would prove fatall and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to Jeſuits and Puritans; but to ſet down an abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity is not to anſwer an Argument: I will therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the unfitneſſe of this Compariſon between Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick and Forraign Tyrants.<note place="margin">The unfitnes of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon between forraign and domeſticke Tyrants.</note> Thoſe Tyrants whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who have a Lawfull Power over us, we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to obey, we are forbidden to reſiſt. For there is no difference between a good Prince and a wicked Tyrant, found in Sacred Scripture; as concerning the honour, reverence, and ſervice we are to give to them. It is not lawfull therefore to draw the Sword againſt them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they who reſiſt, reſiſt God, and get to themſelves damnation. No Law, whether Divine or Humane, hath ſet over us private Tyrants, Spoylers, Domeſtick or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Robbers; in no Obligation therefore are we bound to them, no ſervice do we owe them; neither are we hindered by any reverence of Authority, or neceſſity of Subjection; but that we may ſmite them ſmiting us, and repell the injuries they offer us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:39316:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>So the People reſiſted</hi> Saul <hi>when he would have killed hiſ Sonne,</hi> 1 Sam. 14.45. Ahikam <hi>defended</hi> Jeremy <hi>the Prophet againſt the King</hi> Jehojakim, <hi>when he would have ſlain him,</hi> Jerem. 26.24. <hi>The Captains over Hundreds and the Princes took away</hi> Athaliah <hi>the Tyrant,</hi> 2 Kings 11. <hi>The</hi> Macchabees <hi>defended themſelves and their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, againſt the Macedonian</hi> Tyrants, &amp;c.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">How the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Jonathan from Saul.</note> The People delivered the Sonne of <hi>Saul</hi> from death, (when he was condemned by his Fathers ſentence) not by Arms, but by intreaties: <hi>the People appeale to</hi> Saul <hi>and his own Conſcience, in the preſence of the living God; that laying aſide the account he had of his Oath, he would have an account of the Law; as if they had ſaid, is it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, that he ſhould receive the leaſt harme, who (following God) hath wrought ſo great Salvation for the People?</hi> So <hi>Tremelius</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> in their Annotations upon the place. The <hi>People delivered</hi> Jonathan, <hi>that he might not dye; whom the King ſlew not, being overcome with the inſtant requeſt of the People.</hi> So <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, in 1 <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Ahikam</hi> the cheif Magiſtrate under the King, defends the Prophet, not from the Tyranny of the King, but from the fury of the People; as is evident from the Text.<note place="margin">How Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kam defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Jeremiah</note> The <hi>hand of</hi> Ahikam <hi>was with</hi> Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, <hi>that he might not be delivered into the hand of the People, to put him to death;</hi> the hand of <hi>Ahikam,</hi> that is, (Saith <hi>Tremelius</hi>) the Authority and Help: for <hi>Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kam</hi>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:39316:30"/>had been now a long time Councellor in the Kings Court, and therefore his Authority could do much, thus he. It is one thing to appeaſe the Tumult of the People, by the Authority of the King; and another thing, to riſe up againſt the King in a popular Tumult; that is the duty of a good Man and a faithfull Magiſtrate; this the part of a Rebell and Traytor to his Country. <hi>Of</hi> Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah <hi>I ſhall ſpeak in due place.</hi> The Macchabees, were not lawfully ſubject to the Macedonian Tyrants, and therefore might freely defend themſelves and the Nation, from the incurſions of the Tyrants, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the injury offered them, by force of Arms. Weigh well (ye Academian youth) the ſtrength of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences. The Judges, who (beſides the right of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Government) had a ſpeciall command from God, they ſlew their Enemies. King <hi>Ezekiah</hi> warred againſt the King of Aſſyria. <hi>Jonathan</hi> (at the depreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People) eſcaped the puniſhment of death. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> is delivered by the hand of <hi>Ahikam</hi> the Kings Councellor, from the fury of the People. The Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees defended their Nation from hoſtile invaſion. Therefore the Inferiour Magiſtrate may and ought to reſtraine the King. There is none amongſt you ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull in Logick as not to know, that theſe concluſions do no whit agree with their premiſſes. Theſe vain So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticall Arguments therefore doe blemiſh <hi>Paraeus,</hi> either with groſſe Ignorance, or notorious malice: if he ſees not the Fallacies, he is as blinde as a Mole; but if wittingly and willingly he ſtrives to caſt this miſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your eyes, and the eyes of other young Students, he has the greater ſin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:39316:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>Thraſybulus <hi>caſt out the thirty Tyrants out of</hi> Athens. <hi>The Romans, they baniſht the Kings which ruled wickedly; they compeld the Conſuls to lay down their Magiſtracy: they Judged and depoſed</hi> Nero <hi>and</hi> Maximinus, <hi>who were Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe Examples are onely of Fact, and do not infer any right; and becauſe they are unlike, they conclude nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Electors deprived</hi> Winceſlaus <hi>of the Empire.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>Done it was, I confeſſe, whether done by equity or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, let others determine: let him tell us, that can; What is the Authority of the Imperiall Majeſty? or what is the Power of the Electorall dignity? I am not aſhamed to be ignorant, who have ſpent my time in the ſtudy of Divine, not Politique matters: it was do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> alſo peradventure to the Publique good; but is it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be imitated? Poyſon hath been a Remedy to ſome, which yet the Phyſicians do not number amongſt their wholeſome Medicines.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Trajanus <hi>is prayſed in</hi> Dion, <hi>becauſe, that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39316:31"/>the Sword to the Praefect of the Praetorium, he ſaid; if I command things Juſt, uſe this for me; if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, againſt me.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Trajanus his Speech to the Tribune of the Souldiers approved.</note> 
                        <hi>Paraeus</hi> did not draw the prayſe of <hi>Trajanus</hi> out of the Fountain of <hi>Dion,</hi> but the rivulets of <hi>Bucan;</hi> For <hi>Trajanus</hi> delivered that Sword, not to the Praetorian-Praefect, but to the Tribune of the Souldiers. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was indeed worthy of all prayſe; who freely of his own accord, not by any others compulſion, did that, which was acceptable to God, profitable to the Subjects, and worthy of an Emperour. Theſe and the like favours which Princes vouchſafe of themſelves, do indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to them the affection and good will of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; but confer upon the People, or Inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates no right at all over their Princes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let the judgement alſo of</hi> Luther <hi>be ſeen, and of the Divines, to the Lawyers of</hi> Wittenberge, <hi>concerning this queſtion; and</hi> Peter Martyrs <hi>Commentaries upon</hi> Judges, <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luthers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this queſtion.</note> 
                        <hi>Luther,</hi> and the Divines do ſpeak, not of a King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with an abſolute Power; but of Princes admitted upon condition, which as well the writings of <hi>Luther,</hi> as <hi>Sleidans</hi> Relation of <hi>Luther,</hi> do Witneſſe. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tyrannicall and Idolatrous Kings, thus did <hi>Luther</hi>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:39316:31"/>both teach and write. <hi>What therefore was to be done? were the Kings to be baniſhed out of their Kingdoms? or Forces to be raiſed againſt them? No. They were not to be obeyed, but the greateſt extremities to be ſuffered; which the example of</hi> Daniel, <hi>and of his Companions do declare.</hi> Thus <hi>Luther</hi> in Theſaur. artic. loc. de Magiſtratu. <hi>When the Duke of Saxony and other Princes of the Empire</hi> (ſaith Sleidan) <hi>met together at Smalcaldia, to deliberate concerning: the undertaking a defence againſt the hoſtile violence</hi> (if by chance any ſhould happen) <hi>before the League was entered. There were admitted to the Councell not only Lawyers, but alſo Divines;</hi> Luther <hi>he alwayes taught, that we ought not to reſiſt the Magiſtrate. But when the Lawyers in this deliberation taught, that it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Law, ſomtimes, in ſome caſes to reſiſt; and that they declared, that then the matter was brought to that caſe, of which the Laws amongſt other things makes mention.</hi> Luther <hi>ingenuouſly profeſt, that he knew not this was lawfull, and becauſe the Politicall Laws are not impugned, or abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht by the Goſpell; he ſaid, a League might be entred for a Defence; whether</hi> Caeſar <hi>himſelf, or any other in his name, ſhould make war againſt them.</hi> Hitherto <hi>Sleidan</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the judgement of <hi>Luther.</hi> Neither has the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> any other meaning. This man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dealing with Authors is very ill: that, what they have writ concerning one kind of Polity, ſhould be wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to another, contrary to their Senſe and meaning.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>The Third Propoſition.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is not lawfull for Subjects (meerly private, without a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39316:32"/>Lawfull calling) to take up Arms, either to invade Tyrants before danger; or to defend themſelves againſt them in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; or to revenge themſelves upon them after danger, if they may be defended by the ordinary Power.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are but deceitfull Flatteries, framed to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and everſion of Common-wealths: I will not repeate the Vanity of that diſtinction of Subjects, into private Subjects, and Inferiour Magiſtrates, this hath been ſufficiently diſcuſt before. Whoſoever they are of what name or Title ſoever they be, if they be Subjects, they ought not to riſe up againſt their Superiours, to reſiſt their Lords with Force and Arms, or to remove them from their dignity, or deprive them of their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; becauſe there is no Power given by God, or granted by Man to the Inferiour againſt his Superiour.<note place="margin">How miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous that pretence of a lawfull calling it.</note> The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a Lawfull Calling, opens a gap to all Impiety, and all kind of Injuſtice. It will be an eaſie thing for any Man to pretend this Lawfull Calling, and to accuſe even the beſt Prince of Tyranny: <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> will not ſpare <hi>Moſes. Achitophell</hi> will be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to <hi>David. Jeroboam</hi> a wicked Servant will thruſt out the Son of <hi>Solomon.</hi> A Military fury will lay vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands upon <hi>Alexander Severus.</hi> Yea the Jews have a Law againſt Chriſt the King of Kings, and according to that Law he ought to dye. Grant it <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> that it is lawfull, to reſtrain Kings which Reigne Tyrannically, and then no Kings (by what calling ſoever) will be ſafe. Although they live Holy, and governe Juſtly, yet ſhall they never ſatisfie Seditious Men.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:39316:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Theordinary power oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Divine Law, Reaſon, and Nature.</note>The <hi>Ordinary Power</hi> which <hi>Paraeus</hi> ſuggeſts, doth op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Divine Law, Reaſon and Nature; hath the Son any Power over his Father, though cruell? Have the Servants any Power over their Lord, though churliſh? Hath the Wife any Power over her Husband, though unkind? and is the condition of a King any whit worſe? <hi>Every Power which is of God</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>is an ordinate Power;</hi> but this Power which he calls Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is not Ordinate, which ſubjects the Superiour to the Inferiour; the Head to the Body; the Lord to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; and the King to the Subject. The King is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame over all; if once he admit a Companion, or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, he is no longer King. To this captious Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he hath adjoyned ſome Reaſons, which I will brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly run over.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe this were to take the Sword away from God, and a thing not permitted by the Laws.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>He that takes it away, whether he be a Private Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or Inferiour Magiſtrate, he ſhall ſuffer puniſhment as a Traytor to the Divine and Humane Majeſty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the Subjects are bound to obey a wicked Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whilſt they are not compeld to do any thing againſt God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe Words are not clearly and plainly enough
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39316:33"/>ſet down, which may be underſtood two wayes. Firſt, That the Subjects ought not to obey in thoſe things which the Prince ſhall command againſt God. This I confeſſe to be true; of which there is no controverſie in the Church of God. Secondly, That the People ought not to obey that Prince any longer, in any thing; when once he ſhall command any thing obſtinately againſt God. Which opinion the Jeſuites and Puritans ſtifly maintain, who contend with all the force they may, to perſwade the Subjects, That Kings who do not obſerve the Law of God, or hinder thoſe that are obſervers of it, or be perſecutors of them, and (that I may ſpeak in one Word) who do not governe according to the Preſcript of the Divine Law, they do <hi>(ipſo jure)</hi> loſe their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and deprive themſelves of all Honour, Dignity, and Power. They who liſt to take in this Dunghill, let them reade <hi>Joannes Baptiſta Fichlerus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The names and writings of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchians</note> 
                     <hi>de jure Magiſtrat. &amp; offic. Subdit. fol.</hi> 15. <hi>Franciſcus Fevardentius</hi> upon <hi>Heſter, pag.</hi> 89. <hi>Creſwell in Philopat. pag.</hi> 194. <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias contra Tyrannos, queſt.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 189. The <hi>Tract de jure Magiſtrat. queſt.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 155. <hi>&amp;</hi> 275. <hi>Lambertus Danaeus de Politi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſtiana. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 221. <hi>Joannes Althuſius in Politicis, cap.</hi> 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 146. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 195. Whoſe raging madneſſe all true Catholiques do, and have deteſted. For, <hi>The power of Rule is not foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Grace;</hi> which neither can Goodneſſe conferre, nor Wickedneſſe take away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In which caſe alſo, we muſt rather dye, than unlawfully reſiſt. We have the</hi> Lacedemonians <hi>for an example; who,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39316:33"/>when the Conquer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urs commanded thoſe things which were againſt their Laws and Cuſtoms; they ſaid,</hi> If y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand things more harſh than death, we will rather dye. <hi>And</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>in his Ethicks, doth adviſe, rather to dye, than to ſuffer a Mans ſelfe to be compel'd to diſhoneſt things,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 1.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Reſiſtance of the Superiour unlawfull.</note> Speak out Man, that we may know you: Do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive there is any lawfull Kind of Reſiſtance for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour againſt his Superiour? Chriſt the eternall Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, doth ſimply condemne all unſheathing of the Sword, without the order of authority. <hi>Paul</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of the Law, forbids the Faithfull all reſiſtance. <hi>Peter</hi> the chiefe of the Apoſtles, commands Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to every Creature which hath an higher Power; where, all is ſpoken properly of Superiours, without a difference of good or bad; and to all Inferiours indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, without limitation of either Layity or Clergy, of Order, Degree, or Dignity. <hi>Parae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> therefore doth ill diſtinguiſh here, where the Divine Law admits no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction; the Admonitions of Philoſophers, and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Heathen, may induce to the information of Manners; to the explication of Loyalty, or confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Faith, they availe nothing: in theſe we have a more firme Word of Propheſie, and more famous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Saints: <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evill</hi> (ſaith Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) <hi>of the Ruler of thy People,</hi> Exod. 22.28. <hi>Touch not mine Anoynted</hi> (ſaith David) 1 Cron. 16.22. <hi>Riſe not up againſt the King,</hi> Prov. 30.31. <hi>Who may ſay unto the King, what doſt thou?</hi> Eccleſ. 8.3. <hi>Curſe not the King no not in the heart,</hi> Eccleſ. 10.20. as for Examples;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39316:34"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:39316:34"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:39316:35"/>
                     <hi>David</hi> that famous Prophet, when he had King <hi>Saul</hi> guilty of Impiety, Tyranny, and great wickedneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered into his hands, yet would he not touch him. By which Example, he would inſtruct men, that the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Kings is to be committed to God alone; and that it is not lawfull for any Man, not onely to lift up his hand againſt the Prince; but alſo, to violate that Sacred Majeſty,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſo much as in Word. <hi>Elijah</hi> did not reſiſt, but fly from <hi>Ahab,</hi> that Enemy of Religion; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he ſtir up any to Rebellion. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſawn into two by <hi>Manaſſes; Jeremiah</hi> ſhut up in Priſon; <hi>Daniel</hi> caſt to the Lyons; the three Children thrown into the hot fiery Furnace; <hi>Amos</hi> ſtruct through the Temples; <hi>Zacharias</hi> overwhelmed with Stones at the Threſhold of the Temple; <hi>Peter</hi> Crucified with his Head towards the ground; <hi>James</hi> ſlain by the Sword; <hi>Bartholomew</hi> beate with Clubbs; <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> beheaded; that I ſay nothing of the glorious Company of Martyrs, who have honoured the Church of Chriſt by their holy life, and propagated the fame by their precious death. But what Popular tumult was amongſt them? Who of them was an Author of Rebellion? Which of them put the Inferiour Magiſtrates in minde of this duty, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed their ayde by way of Petition or Appeale? Which of them did either curſe or revile their Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. The Chriſtians of ancient Faith, would not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves againſt the Superiour Power in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the faithfull Brethren; They thought it much better, that the Juſt ſhould ſuffer (though unjuſtly) for true Juſtice ſake; than that they ſhould offer any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the Magiſtrates (under Pretence of feigned Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) though wicked Perſecutors.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:39316:35"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the Example of</hi> David, <hi>refuſing to kill</hi> Saul <hi>a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, when it was in his Power to doe it,</hi> 1 Sam. 24.26.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>When it was in his Power <hi>Paraeus?</hi> That is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly in a Mans Power, which is a Mans Right; ſo that, what he doth, he doth Lawfully. Yea, but David <hi>might have done it Lawfully,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bucan, loc.</hi> 49. <hi>Sect.</hi> 77. yet he would not doe it.<note place="margin">David the greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchians</note> 
                     <hi>David</hi> therefore was herein the worſt of Men, a Violator of the Publick Peace and true Piety, an Enemy of his Country, a Neglector of his Friends, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deſertor of his Duty, who, with one Act, and little or no Labour, by the Death of the Tyrant (whom he might have ſlaine ſafely and juſtly) had delivered the Church from error, the Commonwealth from Tyranny, his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Sufferers from Injury, and himſelfe from Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>David</hi> wanted many Teachers, ſuch as we have (at this Day) abounding amongſt us, as well in the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as in the Roman Church, who might have admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him of this duty; where there as a private Man, yet ſuffering <hi>horrible injury;</hi> or as an Inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, <hi>Inveſted with the ordinary Authority.</hi> Of whom I would aske one queſtion; Whether or no have the Subjects, Private, or ſuch as are placed in Magiſtracy, any greater Right, or Lawfull power againſt the King, than that which <hi>David</hi> had againſt <hi>Saul?</hi> The Authour of that Book called <hi>Vindiciae contra Tyran.</hi> doth affirme, That <hi>David</hi> could doe nothing againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39316:36"/>of the Ordinary Power: becauſe he was not one of the States of the People: whom <hi>Paraeus</hi> alſo in this place ranks with the Common People, and private Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. What? was he a Man famous in Peace, powerfull in Warr, Son in Law to the King, appointed by God for the Kingdome, who went in and out before all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whom all ſo dearely loved, and above all ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and reverenced? And was not he one of the States of the People? This one onely Example (were there not another to be found in Sacred or Prophane Hiſtory) doth demonſtrate by a neceſſary Conſequence; That no private Subject, or publike Magiſtrate hath any lawfull Power againſt the King: whom they may either puniſh with Death, thruſt out of his Kingdome, reduce into Order by violence, or deprive of his Dignity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly, the Arguments brought in the beginning for the negative part, do all tend to this, and only confirme this Propoſition of the duty of Chriſtians, who are meerely pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>Againſt theſe Poſitions which <hi>Paraeus</hi> undertook to prove, (and I beleive will prove,<note n="*" place="margin">That is never.</note> 
                     <hi>ad Graecas Calendas</hi>) he brought in the beginning of this Queſtion, ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Sacred Scripture, <hi>viz. Rom.</hi> 13.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Math.</hi> 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. All which he will have to be Spoken and Underſtood of meerely pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Men. <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo found out this very way of eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: for after he had heapt up diverſe Precepts, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39316:36"/>out of both Teſtaments for Obedience he blows all away as it were at one blaſt. <hi>Of private Men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I alwayes ſpeak; for if there be any popular Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, appointed for the moderating the licenciouſneſſe of Kings (ſuch as were in times paſt the Ephori, Tribuni, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marchi, and which power is enjoyed by the three States in every Kingdom, when they ſit in the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">That is, in Parliament.</note> 
                     <hi>chiefe Aſſembly) I am ſo farre from forbidding ſuch, to reſtraine that raging licentiouſneſſe of Kings; that I affirme, if they winke at Kings, who rage and inſult over the poore Commons, they are not guiltleſſe of wicked treachery, Jnſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>ſect.</hi> 31. <hi>Beza</hi> followes <hi>Calvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. There is no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>propounded to private Men ſubject to a tyrant, but amendement of life, and Prayers, and Teares, which the Lord in his time will not deſpiſe.</hi> But as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe Popular Officers, he anſwers in theſe words; <hi>This burden is layd upon the Superiour powers (ſuch as are the</hi> Septemviri <hi>in the Roman Empire, whom they call Electors; and the State of the Kingdome in almoſt all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies) that they reſtraine the raging Tyrants; which if they do not, they ſhall anſwer for their perſidiouſneſſe as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayers of their Country.</hi> Thus <hi>Beza in Conf. c.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 171.172. the Author of that Book called <hi>Vindiciae cont. Tyran.</hi> followes <hi>Beza:</hi> whoſe Words are theſe, <hi>Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Kingdome was not of this world, fled into Ægypt, and withdrew himſelfe from tyranny. Paul, becauſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the duty of every Chriſtian, and not of Magiſtrates, he teacheth to obey even Nero himſelfe. qu.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 203. 204. From this Fellow, of an unknowne Name, did <hi>Lamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Danaeus</hi> draw his Polity. <hi>In a godly Common-wealth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Iudgment upon the Supreame Magiſtrate doth not belong to any one private man in the Common-wealth,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39316:37"/>not to one or other only of the Iudges, Magiſtrates, or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Kingdome; but to the whole States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. &amp;c. de Politia Chriſtiana lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 413. <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> drawes this cord longer yet, and that which others attribute to all in generall, he to each one in particular. <hi>The Subjects</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall not rightly withdraw their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; yet notwithſtanding, they who are in any part parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the adminiſtration of the common-wealth, as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Senators, Conſuls, States, or Tribes, ought to moderate the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolence of Princes, loco.</hi> 49. <hi>Sect.</hi> 76.</p>
                  <p>After him, in the next yeare following, wrote <hi>Joannes Althuſius,</hi> Doctor of both Laws, that, <hi>All the Ephori to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are the Supream Magiſtrates Superiors, when repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the people, they doe any thing in the peoples name; But each of them ſeverall is the Magiſtrates inferior. de Politicis cap.</hi> 14. <hi>pag.</hi> 142. and afterwards, <hi>The people have not the power of puniſhing the Magiſtrate; but the States only. pag.</hi> 161. Peradventure from him <hi>Paraeus</hi> borrowed that diſtinction, not from <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian, Nazianzen, Chryſoſtome, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Hierome,</hi> or any other of the Fathers, of the firſt or middle Age of the Church. <hi>Gregory</hi> (not the Great, but the wicked) <hi>Hildebrand</hi> delivered this burning Firebrand to our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Divines.<note place="margin">The divers names of the uſurped pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> Obſerve (ye Academians) amongſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Men, the divers Names of this uſurped Power. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> hath it, <hi>the popular Magiſtrates;</hi> Beza, <hi>the Superiour powers;</hi> Junius Brutus, <hi>the Nobles of the Kingdom;</hi> Bucan, <hi>the partakers of publick Adminiſtration;</hi> Althuſius, <hi>the Ephori;</hi> Paraeus, <hi>the Inferiour Magiſtrates.</hi> So that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe Authors, I finde ſo many Names of that Power, as there are Heads of that Beaſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.1. But letting Names paſſe, let us ſearch into the Thing ir
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39316:37"/>ſelfe. Peter long ſince ſaid, <hi>be ye Subject to the King as Supreame.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. fy, St. Peter, fy! the King is not Supreame! the Inferiour Magiſtrates are Supreame! thoſe Magiſtrates cenſorious Rod is ever to be feared by the King, being ordained for his Correction, Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or Death; according as the Wrath of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Nobility, or the Fury of the Provoked Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſhall ſuggeſt. But howſoever the matter is, it ſhall be more ſafe to erre with St. Peters ſpirit, than to be otherwiſe opinioned with thoſe Men. With your leave therfore <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> what Optatus Milevitanus wrote long ſince of Donatus, may I affirme of thoſe Ephori. <hi>Since there is none above the Emperor, but God alone who made the Emperor; whilſt the Inferior Magiſtrates do exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above the Emperor, they do as it were exceed the bounds of men; by eſteeming of themſelves as God, in not reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him; who, after God, is to be feared of men de ſchiſm. Donat. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 85. which how well, and according to the Rules of a Common-wealth this done, I appeale to your own Conſcience Paraeus, and ſo haſten to your laſt Propoſition.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>The fourth Propoſition.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet is it lawfull for Subjects meerely private, in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent danger, to defend them and theirs againſt a Tyrant, as againſt a private Robber; if the Tyrant ſhall offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt them as a Robber or Raviſher; they not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the poſsibility of imploring the ordinary power; or any other means to avoid the danger.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:39316:38"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>Monſtrous Doctrine! altogether unworthy to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, or to be refuted. Neither did it become <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeus</hi> (ancient in years, and famous for learning) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Reader, with an undiſcreet confuſion of things, which are moſt disjoyned, and ought to be conſidered in a different reſpect. A Surgeon runns a man thorow, the ſame thing in the ſame manner is done by a Robber; the one deſerves a Reward, the other a Haltar. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Prince doth the ſame thing, and in the ſame manner that the Spoyler; as often as by force of Arms he reduceth into order an obſtinate Enemy of the State, but not both by the ſame Right; becauſe the Prince hath his Sword for revenge, which the Spoyler doth uſurpe for Rapine. Whoſoever therefore ſhall ſay, the Subject hath the ſame Right over the Prince that puniſheth, that the Traveller hath over the Robber that ſpoyleth, he hath no forehead. But the Prince of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth violence to ſome man, upon a cauſe not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly juſt, and lawfull; yea altogether unjuſt and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; namely, Saul to David, and the innocent Prieſts; David, to Uriah; Ahab, to Naboth; Joaſh, to Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah; Manaſſes, to Iſaiah; Pilate to Chriſt; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, Theodoſius to the Theſſolonians. Under Saul, David, Ahab, Joaſh, Manaſſes, liv'd Preiſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets famous for their holineſſe, inſpired with the holy Spirit. Under Chriſt liv'd Zachaeus, and Nichodemus; Inferior Magiſtrates, men pious, and expert in Sacred and Politicall matters. No age brought forth more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or more orthodoxe Biſhops and Prieſts, then under
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39316:38"/>
                     <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> yet have they not made known to us this way of avoiding the Violence of Tyranny. It is, ſhall be, and hath been the common opinion of all Catholicke men, agreable to the Writings of the Prophets, the Precept of Chriſt, the doctrine of the Apoſtles, and the practiſe of Chriſtians; that, the King which ſins, hath God alone to take vengeance, from whom alone he takes his being; whoſe Court he cannot decline, and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he cannot elude; he ought not to be violated by men, although he degenerate into a Tyrant, and abuſe that power which he hath received from God. Which ſeeing it is ſo, it remains, that I weigh well what remains of your new Divinity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe, againſt whom defence by the Magiſtrate is lawfull, againſt them private defence is lawfull in caſe of neceſsity; when that which is done by the Magiſtrate cannot be had, becauſe then, the Laws arme them alſo, who are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men. But in caſe of neceſsity defence is lawfull, by the Inferior Magiſtrate againſt the Superior, and by the Superior againſt the Inferior. Therefore, alſo then pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate defence is lawfull.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of this reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate defence.</note> 
                     <hi>Paraeus</hi> follows his old wont. He confounds things different, and unlike, as if they were the ſame, and by comparing things different, he cunningly draws the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Reader into the Trappe. Thoſe things which are invol'd by him in a multitude of words, I will declare
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39316:39"/>more plainly. The ſonne hath the ſame Power over the Father, that he hath over the Servant; the Wife over the Husband, which ſhe hath over the Handmayde; the Servant over the Maſter which he hath over the Slave; the Marriner over the Ship-Maſter which he hath over the Pirate; The Subject over the Prince, which the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller hath over the Robber. He that proves this, ſhall be crown'd with Hellobore, and drinke till he ſurfeit, <hi>The purging Iuice that whole Anticyra affords.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which follows; concerning the threefold Power of the Superiour againſt the Inferiour, and the Inferiour againſt the Superiour, and of private revenge againſt them both, is turned over and over, and with it's confuſed turnings, exceeds my capacity, neither have I what to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Yet the Divine Law hath; which is the Rule of our words and actions, which no man ought to ſwerve from. Concerning the King it is commanded, <hi>Deſtroy him not, for who can lay his hand on the Lords anointed &amp; be guiltleſſe?</hi> 1 Sam. 26.9. Chriſt the eternall Law-giver, and the faithfull Interpreter of the Law given; The Apoſtles whom Chriſt endued with the graces of the Holy Spirit, and with infallibility of Judgement, for the direction of all Chriſtians: The truely Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Men, and all Chriſtians, who in the time of the ten Perſecutions, have illuſtrared the whole World with their Faith and Charity, and ſealed the Orthodoxe Doctrine with their Blood: Chriſt, (I ſay) the Apoſtles, and Apoſtolicall Men, all patiently ſuffered Kings moſt infamou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for their Tyranny, Wickedneſſe, and Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and not onely patiently ſuffered, but alſo performed all Honour and Reverence to them; and taught all indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently to doe the ſame, by Word and Example; <hi>Not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39316:39"/>for wrath, but for Conſcience ſake,</hi> as in the preſence of the living God, who alone is the Witneſſe <hi>(greater then all exception)</hi> of their innocency, and free Subjection. That which Chriſt taught, and did, a Chriſtian ought not to gainſay; and if he doe (were he an Angell) he ſhall incurre the heavy courſe of an Anathema.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The King that Steward which the Lord, not the Servant may caſt out.</note>Beſides, the King is the Miniſter of God, and that great Steward, which Chriſt hath ſet over his whole Family. If that Steward ſhall beginne (as that wicked Servant in the Goſpell) to deſpiſe his Lord, to neglect his duty, to ſmite his Fellow-Servants, to eate, drinke and be drunken: it is not in the power of the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, not of the Pope, not of the States of a Kingdome, not of the promiſcuous Vulgar (if they be in the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Chriſt) to remove the Steward, conſtituted, and for over them all, by their Lord; the comming of him, that appointed him, is to expected; who alone can call the Steward to account, and put him out at his pleaſure. Therefore <hi>(Paraeus)</hi> you do talke in vaine, of a lawfull Means to depoſe Kings. <hi>queſt.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 49. Yet neither can commend the Author nor deſigne the Executor, nor determine the forme thereof. I inquire for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour in the Word of God, not in your Commentary's; which being without witneſſe, is without Reaſon and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no beleife. I deſire the executour, not confirmed by humane Appointment, but by Divine Authority. <hi>It is Adulterate, Impious, and Sacrilegious (ſaith Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) which is inſtituted by humane preſumption, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ordinance ſhould be violated.</hi> That which you incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate concerning the Brethren of the Kingdome, is a meere Dotage, and has no being but in your braine. God is not the Authour of this Anarchy, neither may man be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39316:40"/>the Executor. One man compared with another, is either his Superiour, his Equall, or his Inferiour: the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour is no way's Subject to the Inferiour; the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour is every way Subject to the Superiour, and an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall has no Rule over his Equall. That the matter may be the more evident in this Suppoſition, view well the Jewiſh Polity,<note place="margin">The manner of the Jewiſh Polity.</note> with the degrees and order thereof; the Decurians are above the people; the Quinquagenari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans above the Decurians; above them, the Centurians, over whom the Tribunes bear rule; over them the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Elders; of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> alone is Judge: who is Subject neither to each ſeverall, nor to all joyntly, but to God alone. <hi>He himſelfe</hi> (that I may uſe the words of Ambroſe) <hi>was held by no Laws, becauſe Kings are free from the bonds of offences; and are not cal'd to puiſhment by any Laws being, ſecure in the power of their Empery.</hi> Thus he upon the 50 Pſalme.</p>
                  <p>As concerning the Meane themſelves; I deny not, but that there are ſome ordained by Chriſt; which the Saints long ſince have uſed,<note place="margin">The meanes to avoyd or deſtroy Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</note> and Chriſtians ought alwayes to uſe: ſuch as are Flight, Patience, Prayers and Teares. Chriſt himſelfe ſought his ſafety by Flight; The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs offer'd up their Soules to God with patience, and by Patience the Confeſſours preſerv'd the Faith entire. By Prayers the Sons of the Church have ſtill over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown the Tyrants, whoſe Enſigne-Bearer, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Lords Hoſt Saint Ambroſe has theſe words. <hi>I know not how to warre, I know how to greive. I can weepe, I can mourne; againſt Arms, Souldiers, Gothes, my teares are my we apons, otherways I neither can nor ought to reſiſt.</hi> In his Oration againſt <hi>Auxentius,</hi> poſt Epiſt. 32. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil the great well appointed for Battell, <hi>I will not</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39316:40"/>he) <hi>betray the Faith through the loſſe of Goods, through Baniſhment or Death; I have no wealth more than a torne Garment, and a few Bookes; I ſojourne on Earth, as ever about to leave it; my weake Body having received one ſtripe, will over come the ſenſe of Paine and all Torments.</hi> In <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicer. theatr.</hi> hiſtoric. pag. 154.</p>
                  <p>To him adhears <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> no light-armed Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, <hi>When I was driven from the City, I ſaid within my ſelfe, if the Queen will have me a Baniſhed Man, let her baniſh me: the Earth is the Lords and the fulneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and if ſhe will cut me into two, let her cut me;</hi> Iſaiah <hi>ſuffer'd the like, if ſhe will caſt me into the Sea, I will call to mind</hi> Jonah: <hi>if ſhe will caſt me into the Furnace, the three Children ſuffer'd the ſame: if ſhe will throw me to the Wild Beaſts, let her throw me, I will remember</hi> Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>caſt into the Den of Lyons. If ſhe will ſtone me, let her ſtone me; I have</hi> Stephen <hi>the Proto-Martyr my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. If ſhe will take away my head, let her take it; I have</hi> Iohn Baptiſt <hi>my Companion; and if ſhe will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my Subſtance, let her take it; naked came I out of my Mothers wombe and naked ſhall I returne.</hi> in Epiſt. ad <hi>Cyriacum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let <hi>Bernard</hi> that ſtout Champion come upon the Stage; <hi>Whatſoever you pleaſe to doe with your Kingdome, with your Soul, and your Crown; we the Sonns of the Church can by no means diſſemble the injury's, contempt, and tramp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon our Mother. Verily we will ſtand and fight unto Death (if need be) for our Mother, with thoſe arms that are lawfull, not with ſhields and with ſwords, but with prayers and teares unto God.</hi> Epiſt. 221. Thoſe men ſcarce ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for Glory in the <hi>(Heavenly)</hi> Country, unleſſe it were by patience in the way <hi>(on Earth:)</hi> they would not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39316:41"/>Members under a thorny Head. Since <hi>Paraeus</hi> is conceited otherwiſe, let him raiſe himſelfe a Ladder, that he may climbe up to Heaven alone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <stage>The ſecond Reaſon.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe, to take away publicke or private defence, againſt the horrible cruelty of Tyrants, were to confirme their licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe infinite; whereby civill Society would be plainly deſtroy'd, and eſpecially the Church, becauſe the worſe part would take away the better.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Publique or private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by Arms, how dangerous.</note> The ſecond Reaſon, is grievous to Kings, unproſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to Subjects, and odious to all Peaceable Men; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will make the multitude ſo inſolent and unruly, that they will obey neither the Laws, nor their Kings, if they ſhall diſpleaſe them, and will open not a Window onely, but even a large Gate to men, for the ſtill devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and attempting new Matters, under the pretence of reſtoring the Common-Wealth. For the reverence of Supreame Power being taken away, and Majeſtie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn'd, wicked hands will ſoone be upon any man, and the beſt Kings ſhall periſh by the ſame fate, that Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; So in humane things there ſhall be nothing kept ſacred, or inviolate; as the Ancients have obſerved, and they who are now alive do perceive and bewaile. The Society of men is made firme, and the communion of Saints preſerved not by Humane Prudence, but by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39316:41"/>Providence; that it cannot be deſtroyed by any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of Tyranny. He that is our God doth permi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny when and how long he will's; and doth diſpoſe of the Miniſtry of Tyrants to the Puniſhment of Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Tryall of Faith: Neither is he leſſe mercyfull and gracious, when he caſtneth our offences by cruell Tyrants, for the ſalvation of the periſhing Soule; than when he beſtow's Bleſſings upon us by mercyfull Princes, for the comfort of this preſent Life. Neither can the worſe part take away the better; becauſe God will not give his holy ones <hi>as a prey unto their teeth,</hi> who caſts his Veſſell into the Furnace of Tribulation, to ſtrengthen not to breake it. and Tyranny doth keepe under <hi>Gods people,</hi> that they may be preſſed for their amendment, not oppreſſed for their ruine; whence <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaith, <hi>As often as Tyrants ſit at the ſterne of the Common-Wealth, or cruell Lords adminiſter the Houſhold affaires, the wrath of God is to be appeaſed, by holy Prayer, and ſerious amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Life; and a mitigation of the preſent difficulties and troubles is to be prayed for.</hi> Thus he, de provident. ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. 7. which good and wholeſome Remedy the ancient Chriſtians had try all of, whoſe Glory was in the Croſſe,<note place="margin">How the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans behaved themſelves under Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</note> and whoſe Triumph was in Patience; who as long as they could, they willingly enjoyed the benefit of Life; and when they could not, they willingly endured the ſharpeneſſe of Death; alwayes faithfull to their God, in under going Martyrdome, leaſt they ſhould offend the Divine Majeſty: Loyall to the King; not, in doing the Sinne he commanded, but in ſuffering the Puniſhment he inflicted. <hi>Paraeus,</hi> he deſcribes a Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe; wherewith, as it were with a Butchers Knife, he cuts off the King from the Common-Wealth,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39316:42"/>and makes the inferiour Members to rule over the Head, even againſt Nature; by ſubjecting the Supreame Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to the ordinary Power of the Inferiour Magiſtrate, and when this Power cannot be implored, to the private revenge of the Tumultuous People which Remedy God did neither inſtitute before the Law, nor eſtabliſh in the Law, nor vouchſafe by the Prophets, nor reveal by Chriſt, nor promulge by the Apoſtles, nor publiſh by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Fathers, nor decree by Orthodox Councells, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I the more wonder, that this man, (of no ſmall lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and verſt in the Sacred Scriptures, Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory) ſhould ſo raſhly turne aſide from the Law of God, the Goſpell of Chriſt, the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, and opinion of the purer Church, to the errour of the Modern Anti-Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>David Paraeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Without doubt, the Law of God doth not ſo eſtabliſh the licentiouſneſſe of Tyrants, that in the meane time humane ſociety be deſtroyed</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor Owen.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> God ſhall henceforward ſit idle in Heaven, neither ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king care of the Earthly Kingdomes, nor holy Church; let all periſh, and come to ruine, if the Ambitious States, or Seditious Commons do not come in to helpe. What elſe is this, but to exalt the Arm of Fleſh, the Wiſdome of this World, the humane (that I may not ſay Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh) Power above God himſelfe, and againſt his divine
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39316:42"/>Ordinance; to the ſubverſion of Piety, the deſtruction of Peace, and ruine of all Common-Wealth. All Lawes are either given by God, or eſtabliſhed by Man, that men may live peaceably and holily in a Common-wealth; and that thoſe things may be avoyded which doe hinder either Peace or Holineſſe, I appeale to your own Conſcience <hi>Paraeus,</hi> is it not better, ſafer, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curer, to the propogation of piety, and preſervation of peace, to ſuffer the Tyranny of one (though more cruell than <hi>Nero</hi>) than to ſet all the Members of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth at odds, and to caſt the whole State upon the greateſt and moſt certain Dangers. For the King cannot be ſo deſtitute and forlorne, but that he will have many of the States of his Kingdome to be joyned with him, and companions of his wickedneſſe; with whoſe helpe he being aſſiſted, he cannot forcibly be reduced un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to order, without bloody Slaughters, and the publike Calamity. But a Kingdome never becomes ſo miſerable under that King, though moſt cruell, as for the moſt part it happens to be, in a civill Warre;<note place="margin">Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the order of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority.</note> So that God ſeems in nothing more to have provided for the publike good, than by ſetting the Superiour above the Inferiour, and ſubjecting the Inferiour to the Superiour; that no man preſume to riſe up againſt the King, whom God hath placed above all; and being ſo placed he hath not left to humane Tryall, but reſerved to his divine Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He blaſphemes therefore againſt Heaven, who attempts evil in heart, mouth, or hand, againſt a Tyrant juſtly poſſeſt of his Kingdome.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>And thus farre concerning the Propoſitions of <hi>Paraeus,</hi> and the Reaſons of them, not good and well applyed Reaſons but weake and frivolous; framed to the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39316:43"/>of the People, and ruining of Kings, and their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. I will now returne, to the confirming the truth of my Aſſertion concerning the abſolute power of Kings.</p>
               <p>Thoſe men agree well amongſt themſelves concerning the thing; it is concerning the manner, that <hi>Bellarmino Danaeus</hi> and <hi>Paraeus</hi> do contend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither may we ſee the contrary in the reſt of the Followers of both Sects. I inſiſt onely upon theſe three becauſe they are of ſo great note amongſt their followers, that none of the Papiſts will contradict <hi>Bellarmino;</hi> none of the Puritans gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay <hi>Danaeus</hi> and <hi>Paraeus:</hi> Know theſe and know all.</p>
               <div n="1" type="reason">
                  <head>The firſt Reaſon of the abſolute power of Kings, from the Dictate of Nature.</head>
                  <p>Nature it ſelfe doth oppoſe this Puritan-Papiſticall Tenet: from which fountain, the Authority of Rule, the Neceſſity of Obedience; the Honeſty of Life, the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and puniſhment of Vice; the goodneſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Vertue do ſtreame forth. And thoſe Wiſe Men (whoſe Prudence in making Laws Antiquity ſo much admires) diſcerning good from evill, juſt from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, honeſt from diſhoneſt have publiſhed moſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Laws. Whence <hi>Baſil</hi> the great: <hi>The Princes of the whole Earth are ſacred, even for the propriety of nature it ſelfe to good; who her ſelfe beſtows this Empery upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> in pſal. 44. <hi>In this,</hi> ſaith Cyprian, <hi>whole Nature doth agree: there is one King to the Bees, one Captaine among the Flocks, one Governour among the Herds,</hi> de vanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Idol.</p>
                  <p>St <hi>Ambroſe</hi> (lib. 6. cap. 21. concerning the works of the ſix Dayes) he obſerves an admirable diſpenſation
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39316:43"/>of Nature in the hives of Bees. <hi>Bees defend their Kings with the chiefeſt protection, they think it honourable to dye for the King; the King being inſafety they alter not their judgement, they change not their mind; the King being loſt they forſake their faith of keeping their offices; becauſe he who had the principallity is ſlaine.</hi> The ſame hath <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome.</hi> lib. 1 epiſt. 3. Let him that fights againſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs goe to the Bees, let him conſider their wayes that he may learne to <hi>feare God and honour the King.</hi> From the dictate of Nature, I haſten to the Law of Nations the Lawyers call that the Law of Nations which is equally obſerved by all Nations. Whence <hi>Auguſtine; It is a generall covenant of humane ſociety, to obey their Kings.</hi> confeſſ, lib. 3. cap. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="reason">
                  <head>The ſecond Reaſon of the immunity of Kings from the Law of Nations.</head>
                  <p>Although the Acts of Ancient Kings, for a great part of them are loſt by the injurie of the Times, or ſloth of Men; yet from them that are extant in the Reliques of Hiſtoryes, it will evidently appear, both that all Nations have obeyed their Kings, and that all Kings have excer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed an abſolute Authority, circumſcribed with no bounds of conditions. Let the Annalls of all Nations be turned over, it ſhall no where be found, that ſuch a bridle is caſt over Kings; that they muſt ſubmit their ſcepters to the will of the People; or that they ſhould receive from the Nobles, a Law to moderate their Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Juriſdiction. Which thing <hi>Cicero</hi> hath obſerv'd in his oration for King <hi>Deiotarus,</hi> before <hi>Caeſar</hi> moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in the Law and Hiſtory<hi>'s. It is ſo unuſuall a thing</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:39316:44"/>(ſaith the Oratour) <hi>for a King to be guilty of a capitall crime, that before this time it was never heard of. Artaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> alſo Vice-Roy of Perſia (not without a Jeere, deriding the lightneſſe of the Graecians) mocked <hi>Themiſtocles: You Grecians</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>care for nothing more than Liberty and Equallity; but we Perſians do think it moſt excellent, and moſt ſacred of all things, to give Honour and Reverence to the King, as to the Image of the living God; who rules and governs this whole World.</hi> What <hi>Artabanus</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the inſtinct of Nature, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and others of the Ancients delivered by the inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſayings, produced in their place will have the more Weight.</p>
                  <p>That which thoſe Politicall Divines do ſo often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate concerning the Lacedemonians, Athenians, and Romans, is a meere dreame. After that <hi>Theopompus,</hi> the laſt King of the Spartans had joyned to his Sonne, and his future Succeſſors, the <hi>Ephori;</hi> the name of King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an empty Title amongſt the Lacedemonians; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving altogether loſt the authority, which before <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pompus</hi> all the Kings had abſolute and moſt free. The Athenians after that they ceaſed to be under Kings, they endured no kind of Government long, being impatient of the preſent, and deſirous of new; at length they were ruined by an Anarchy. The People of Rome bewiched with the ſweetneſſe of liberty, after the example of the Graecians, they changed their Kingdome into a Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy; and eſtabliſhed a Law, never to reduce their Kings. But by their forraigne Warres, and civill Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords they learnt at laſt, that there was no Remedy for their decaying Country, but to be governed by one. Therefore they created a dictator, of a free Power and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39316:44"/>Rule; free from giving any account of his Words and Actions; from whom there ſhould be no appeale, and to whom was permitted to impriſon, puniſh with bonds, or death, any man of the Nobles, or of the Patrician Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the cauſe not declared.</p>
                  <p>What the Puritans have deviſed concerning the States of the Kingdom in England, France, and Scotland, I dare not call them old wives fables, ſince that they are ſhamful lyes ſo lately broached. For how great the Power, and how ſacred the Majeſty of our Kings is, I had rather draw from the full fountain of the ancient Parliaments of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of men moſt expert in the Laws of England, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in former ages; then from the muddy ſtanding pooles of Modern Politicks. There is in <hi>Thomas</hi> de <hi>Walſingham,</hi> an Epiſtle in the name of the whole Kingdome, from the Parliament held at Lincolne, about the Yeare 1301. inſcribed to the Romane Biſhop; wherein the Lords Spirituall and Temporall, with all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons doe ſpeake to the Biſhop concerning the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of the King of England in theſe words following; <hi>We know (moſt holy Father) and it is a thing notorius, from the firſt inſtitution of the Kingdome of England as well in the times of the Brittains as of the Engliſh, that certaine and direct power of Rule hath belonged to the King; and that the Kings of England by the free preheminence of the Royall Dignity, and by the cuſtome obſerved at all times, have not anſwered, neither ought to anſwer any thing, before any Eccleſiaſticall or Secular Judge, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> de <hi>Bracton</hi> Lord Cheife Juſtice of the Kings Bench (under <hi>Henry</hi> the third) a Man moſt learned in the Engliſh Laws, hath theſe words; <hi>There are under
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39316:45"/>the King free men and ſervants; and all under him, and he under none, but God onely. If a man be injured by the King; (ſince no urit can run againſt the King) there is place left for petition, that he would correct and amend his fact: if he do not, it ſhall be a ſufficient puniſhment, that he may expect God his avenger; Concerning Royall Charters, or the Acts of Kings, neither private perſons nor Juſtices ought to diſpute.</hi> This is cited in that Oration of the moſt honourable Lord <hi>Eliſmer,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Bareley,</hi> late Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of England; moſt expert in the Laws of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; which oration he made in the Exchequer chamber in the yeare 1609. pag. 108. it is cited alſo by the Lord Biſhop of Rocheſter de uſurp, pontif. poteſt. lib. 1. cap. 8</p>
                  <p>What was the authority of the States of France, in former times over their Kings which offended, <hi>Paſqueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> doth relate, lib. 1. antiquit. Gallic. <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11. did urge the Senatours and Councellours, that they would be the Authours of a certain Edict, which they refuſed to doe, becauſe it ſeemed to be unjuſt. The King full of wrath, threatned death to the whole Senate; <hi>Vacarius</hi> the Preſident of the Councell, approched the King with the whole Senate clothed in Purple; the King aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at the comming of the Senate all in Purple; he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, wherefore they came and what they would? <hi>Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> anſwered for them all, <hi>We ſeek for death, which thou ſo wrathfully threatned us with: Know this, O King! we will aſſuredly dye, rather than do any thing againſt our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and duties.</hi> Thus <hi>Paſquerius.</hi> Thoſe States had learned, not to puniſh the King offending; but to lay down their lives at the will and command of the King, And in their generall Councell held at Paris
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39316:45"/>
                     <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1614. it was propounded; <hi>That there was no earthly power, ſpirituall or temporall, which hath any right over the Kings of France, to remove the ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Kings from their dignity, or to abſolve their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Loyalty and Obedience, which they for ever owe them, upon any cauſe or pretence whatſoever,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When the Scotch Nobility had endeavoured Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt <hi>Ferchardus</hi> the moſt wicked King of the Scots, <hi>Colmannus</hi> the Biſhop did reſtrain them, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the King; that the divine vengeance would ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overtake him: The King a while after being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at a hunting, &amp; ſick of the louſie diſeaſe, he cryed out; That all the evills were befalne him, becauſe he hearkned not to the holy Biſhop, when he ſo well admoniſhed him. Afterwards <hi>Colmannus</hi> comforting him he repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and quietly departed. Well done, good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Biſhop! Thou recalledſt the People and Nobles from Inſurrection, thou repreſſedſt the Seditious, thou didſt openly admoniſh the King, and that modeſtly, yet freely too; thou didſt not doe it privily with raylings to the ſtirring up the people; Thou perſwadedſt, that he is not to be chaſtiſed at the pleaſure of the States, but left to the divine Revenge. I will adde ſome heads of the Royall Law among the Scots out of <hi>Hector Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi> lib. 12.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>In profane matters, let no man determine the Law, but whom the Royall Majeſty ſhall appoint.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Let all Law be determined, Aſſemblies cited, Councells called in the name of the King alone.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Let no man obtain the Magiſtracy, by any other than the Kings authority.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:39316:46"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If any man ſhall ſweare Allegiance to any but the King, let the crime be Capitall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Let no man poſſeſſe ground, farme, or field by any other then the Royall Authority.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If any man ſhall enter league with another, profeſsing faith and loyalty, againſt any man, let him be puniſhed with death.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If any man without the command of the King, ſhall have men in Arms, let him expiate his crime with death.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>If any of the Nobles ſhall contract affinity with thoſe of another Dominion, let him be puniſhed with Death.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe, and more like unto theſe are to be found in <hi>Boe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for other Kings and Kingdomes, let them look to it whom it concerns. So that we have the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall highnes of our Lord and King (then which the Sunne hath not ſeen any thing more juſt, more learned, or more holy,) preſerved whole and entire againſt all the machinations of Papiſts, and of Puritans. Bleſſed be the name of the Lord, who in theſe our day's, (wherein he foreſaw ſo many ſcandalls of Hereticks and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks would ariſe) hath placed King <hi>James</hi> in the height of this Dominion to the comfort of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, the increaſe of the Catholick Faith, and the ſafety of the Churches Peace; that the Royall Power and the Sacerdotall Office may ſtill flouriſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="reason">
                  <head>The third Reaſon of the Royall Prerogative from the authority of the Civill Law.</head>
                  <p>Amongſt the Interpreters of the Civill Law, doe every where meet us, theſe expreſſions of the Emperour, that he is the<note n="a" place="margin">The Emperour doth puniſh his Subjects whereſoever they offend; <hi>and the Reaſon is,</hi> becauſe he is of Right the Lord of the World. <hi>So</hi> Baldus <hi>C. lib. 4. tit. 42. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuehis.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Lord of the World,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Although he be the Vicar of God. Baldus</hi> C. lib. 6. tit. 8. de jure aureorum annulorum.</note> 
                     <hi>Gods Vicar on earth,</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:39316:46"/>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Jacobus Omphalius</hi> lib de officio &amp; poteſt. princip. c. 10</note> 
                     <hi>the living Law,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">
                        <hi>The Prince hath the fulneſſe of Power. Baldus</hi> again lib. 4. tit. 52. de commun. rerum alienat.</note> 
                     <hi>the fulneſſe of Power,</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">
                        <hi>The Prince is free from the Laws, becauſe he is ſubject to none neither is judged by others. Hoſtienſis</hi> Sum. lib. 1. Rubr. 32. de officio legati. and he cites ff. lib. 1. tit. 3. l. 30. where the ſame words are had.</note> 
                     <hi>the free and</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">The King in his Kingdome can do all things, even out of the fulneſſe of power. Corſetus Siculus <hi>tract. de poteſt. Reg. part. 5. num. 66.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Power;</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">He that diſputes concerning the power of the Prince, whether he hath done well, or no; he is ſacrilegious: <hi>So the Marginiſt upon</hi> Angelus Peruſinus <hi>C. lib. 9. tit. 29. de crimine ſacrilegii l. 2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Diſputation concerning the Priviledge of the Prince is ſacrilegious,</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Inſtit. lib. <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>2.</hi> de jure natural. Gent. &amp; civil. <hi>and</hi> Claudius Cantiuncula <hi>in the ſame place.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>that which pleaſeth the King hath the force of a Law,</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">To reſtraine the Supreame Power, belongs to them who neither acknowledge the Imperiall Power, nor how great a diſtance their is between a private fortune, and the Regall Dignity. <hi>Doctores in l. 3. bene a Zenone C. lib. 7. tit. 37.</hi> de quadriennii proſcriptione.</note> 
                     <hi>the power of the Prince is not to be reſtrained,</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">The Prince is bound to no forme, neither is a Reaſon to be required of him, why doſt thou ſo? (<hi>Baldus C. lib. 7. tit. 50.</hi> ſententiam reſcindi non poſſe: <hi>l. 3.</hi> impetrata.) Becauſe ſeeing the King is the Cauſe of Cauſes, a cauſe is not to be required of his power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſince that of the firſt cauſe there is no cauſe giuen. <hi>So Baldus again decret. l. 2. tit. 16.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t lite prudente nihil in novetur. <hi>upon 3 Eccleſ. num. 7.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>if the Prince ſhall do any thing out of the fulneſſe of Power, no man may ſay, why doſt thou ſo?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:39316:47"/>
                  <p>Laſtly, <hi>William Barclay</hi> doth inferre from <hi>Bartolus, Baldus, Paulus, Caſtrenſis, Lodovicus Romanus, Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Felinus, Albericus and others; That the Prince upon certaine knowledge can doe all things, above the Law, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Law, and againſt the Law, the Prince alone may conſtitute an univerſall Law, the Prince oweth an account to God onely. The Prince is free from the Laws. And it is a raſh thing to deſire the Royall Majeſty ſhould be limited with any bounds.</hi> contra Monarchum. l. 3. cap. 14.</p>
                  <p>There are more of this ſort in <hi>Pet. Greg. Tholoſan.</hi> de <hi>Repub.</hi> throughout his ſixt book. In <hi>Adam Blacuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus</hi> in his Apology for Kings <hi>c.</hi> 25. &amp; 31. and in <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Saravia de imperandi authorit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from whence it doth neceſſarily follow, that the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the People is nothing, the authority of the Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Magiſtrate is above the People, but below the King; by whom he is, and to whom he is Subject: but the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all authority is free and abſolute. For that Power is free which cannot be condemned by mans judgement, nor ought to be compelled: and the abſolute power, is (under God) Supreame, in every part perfect, which can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be encreaſed, nor ought to be deminiſhed without offering injury to the divine Diety, becauſe God is the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:39316:47"/>Author and Ordainer of it. For where there is a Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, there is a power of commanding; to the reſt there remains a neceſſity of obeying; as the Lawyers ſpeak.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="reason">
                  <head>The fourth Reaſon from the Cannon Law.</head>
                  <p>Many things are alledged in the behalfe of Kings even from the Cannon Law alſo, againſt the inſolent haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Pope. Firſt it is infer'd; <hi>that the ſecular Princes are not ſubject to the Pope; becauſe God hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Secular affaires not by the Pope, but by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours.</hi> diſt. 8. cap. quo jure. Innocent the third <hi>doth acknowledge the authority of the Kings of France, which he neither intends to diſturbe or deminiſh.</hi> de judiciis cap. Novit. the ſame Pope alſo confeſſeth, <hi>that the ſame King hath no Superiour in temporall things.</hi> qui Filii ſunt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittimi. cap. per venerabilem. Honorius the third <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth himſelfe a fit Judge concerning the birth-day of the Queen of Cyprus: but judgement concerning the right of ſucceſsion (he confeſſeth) doth belong not to the Pope, but to the King.</hi> de ordin. cognit. cap. Tuam. <hi>Allexander</hi> the third, he would not take knowledge of the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſome Engliſh men contending before him, <hi>leaſt he ſhould ſeeme to detract from the right of the King of England.</hi> Qui Filii ſunt legittimi, cap. Cauſam.</p>
                  <p>To whom knowledge concerning the Rights of private men doth not belong; he ought not to judge of Kings, and their Royall Crownes, and Kings who would not acknowledge the Roman Biſhop, (bearing himſelfe the Vicar of Chriſt and the Univerſall Biſhop) their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour; they will not endure the States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39316:48"/>or the promiſcuous multitude (a wilde beaſt of many heads) to be above them. You will ſay, what then? ſhall the Royall Majeſty be immenſe incloſed with no Limits? not liable to be puniſhed by the Pope, nor by the Nobles of the Kingdome, nor at leaſt by the whole multitude? not at all. The King has the place of God on Earth, and hath his authority from Heaven; he acts the Perſon, and beares the Image of the eternall King: to whom alone he is bound to render an account of his words and actions; being ſecure from all conſtraint tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Majeſty of his Royall Dignity. Which I ſhall evince by moſt firme reaſons drawn out of the old and new Teſtament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="reason">
                  <head>The fift Reaſon from ſacred Scripture</head>
                  <p>What High Preiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what Synode of Preiſts; what Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of the Nobles, or what promiſcuous Multitude ever excerciſed the <hi>ordinary Power</hi> againſt <hi>Saul</hi> defiled with all impiety? againſt <hi>David</hi> guilty of Adultery, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? againſt <hi>Solomon</hi> guilty of Poligamy and Idolatry? againſt other Kings of Judah, and Iſrael, miſerably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning the Temple of God, wickedly polluting the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, drawing the People in heapes to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, drunken with the blood of the Prieſts, of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, of the Nobles and all innocent Men; even moſt defiled with all kind of wickedneſſe? <hi>David</hi> he ſpared <hi>Saul,</hi> and becauſe he had cut off the skirt of his Garment, <hi>his heart ſmote him &amp; he greatly trembled. Ieremiah</hi> taught the Captives not to fight againſt the King, but to pray for the King. <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> had by his publicke decree de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated all the Jews unto ſlaughter, at an appointed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39316:48"/>day; the People fortified themſelves with Prayers, with Teares, with Faſting, with Sackcloth and Aſhes; not with Revilings, not with Lyings in wait, not with Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not with Arms. <hi>Mordecai</hi> did not admoniſh the Queen to take away the Tyrant by poyſon, but by faſtings and prayers to God, and humble ſupplication to the King, to avert the heavy falling of that miſcheife which hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over them: which <hi>Buchanan</hi> doth not deny, in whoſe ſeditious dialogue concerning the Right of Kings with the Scots, are theſe words; <hi>The Kings of the Jews were not puniſhed by the Subjects, becauſe from the beginning they were not created by the Subjects, but given them by God, by the beſt right therefore he that was the author of the Dignity, the ſame ſhould be the exactor of puniſhment.</hi> Thus Buchanan.</p>
                  <p>But ſeing he could not well unlooſe this knot; he cut's it into two with the ſword of a Lying tongue; to wit, <hi>That the Scotch Kings are not given by God, but crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the People; and that whatſoever right they challenge to themſelves, they have it from the Commons; and that the Multitude has the ſame right over the Kings which the Kings have over each one of the Multitude.</hi> Tell me <hi>Buchanan,</hi> I pray; why ſhall not the Kings of all other Nations have the ſame immunity that the Jews? they alſo have no Authour, and accknowledge no Authour but God. <hi>Moſes</hi> doth witnes <hi>that God the Creator of the whole World, preſently after the Flood, ordained the Sword to be the avenger of Bloodſhed; and eſtabliſhed Servitude to be the puniſhment of the Father that was mocked.</hi> In which all the parts of civill Juriſdiction, and Royall Power are Synecdochically underſtood. Job alſo doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>that God alone it is who unlooſeth the bond of Kings,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39316:49"/>and girdeth their loynes with a girdle.</hi> I ſuppoſe he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth concerning the Kings of the Gentiles, the Polity of the Jewes, was not as yet conſtituted by the hand of <hi>Moſes, by me Kings raigne, and Princes decree juſtice,</hi> ſaith the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. Chriſt witneſſeth that <hi>Pilat's</hi> power <hi>was given him from Heaven.</hi> Saint Paul hath writ, <hi>that there is no power, but of God. From him is the Emperour, from whom he is Man, before he be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,</hi> ſaith Tertullian. <hi>From him he hath his power, from whom he hath his ſpirit:</hi> And as Irenius hath it. <hi>The Earthly Kingdome is appointed by God for the benefit of the Gentiles, and by whoſe command Men are borne, by his command Kings are made.</hi> Auguſtine is yet more plain and more full. <hi>It is God alone, who gives earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes both to the good and to the bad, and this not raſhly, or as it were by chance, becauſe he is God; but according to the order of things, and of the times; hidden from us, but moſt open to himſelfe.</hi> Thus Auguſtine de Civ. Dei. lib. 4. cap. 33. Yet do the Papiſts and Puritans deviſe many things out of the Scriptures, (a thing uſuall with Hereticks) contrary to the genuine meaning thereof; with which I will not detaine you; they are ſo unſound and unſavory that they will deceive no man, but ſuch an one, as is voyde of Reaſon, or altogether ignorant of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Hiſtory.</p>
                  <p>I have already ſpoken of <hi>Paraeus. Bellarmine, and Danaeus,</hi> do moſt of all inſiſt upon Examples of the tenne Tribes who revolted from their naturall King to a man of ſervile condition of the Men of Libnah, and the Edomites, who rebel'd againſt <hi>Joram.</hi> And of the Kings <hi>Amaziah, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> and of the Queeen <hi>Athaliah,</hi> to which I anſwer: The defection of the tenne Tribes
<pb facs="tcp:39316:49"/>from their naturall King to <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> the Rebellion of the Edomites, and of the men of Libnah; and the ſlaughter of <hi>Amaziah</hi> by the men of Jeruſalem, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Truth of the thing done, but not the equity of the fact, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> moſt truly. <hi>We may not therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a thing muſt be done, becauſe we reade that it hath been done; leaſt we violate the Precept, whilſt we follow the Example.</hi> In the Hiſtory of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> and <hi>Athaliah,</hi> I ſee no difficulty; nothing is there done, which is not according to the equity of Reaſon, and the preſcript of the Law. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> being diſeaſed could not be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in the affaires of the Kingdome; by reaſon of the contagiouſneſſe of his diſeaſe he is removed from the company of the Courtiers, and aſſembly of the People. In the mean while his Sonne govern's the Common-wealth in his Fathers ſtead, yet before the death of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah,</hi> he neither affected the name nor aſſumed the title of King. And as for <hi>Athaliah, Jehoida</hi> the Chiefe Preiſt ſhewed the ſurviving Sonne of the deceaſed King (whom he had ſix yeares hid from the fury of <hi>Athaliah,</hi> the Murdereſſe of the Royal ofspring) to the Princes and Centurions whom he had gathered together at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. They all acknowledge the Child their true King; being ſo acknowledged they crown him, being crowned they ſalute him with joyfull acclamations, <hi>God ſave the King:</hi> after that, neither by their own, nor by the Prieſtly Authority, but in the name of the lately crown'd King they depoſed <hi>Athaliah,</hi> as guilty of Treaſon and Murder, by force and arms. <hi>Jehoiada</hi> acted the chiefe part, but not as chiefe Prieſt, but as chiefe of the Tribe of Levi, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ancient in yeares, expert in the divine Law, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent againſt the dangers which are imminent, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39316:50"/>of the young King and the next Kinſman. The law of God doth not permit to touch Kings with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hand, to revile them with a rayling tongue, or to thinke of them with a malicious heart. The Goſpell of Chriſt forbids reſiſting. Tyrants; <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid reſiſting Perſecutors and Slayers of Chriſtians. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> anſwers, that Laicks of what order or digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſoever they are, are thus bound by the Law, Goſpell and Apoſtolicall Precepts, but not the Roman Biſhop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Vicar of Chriſt, and the univerſall Lord of the whole World for which he is ſtiled by <hi>Danaeus,</hi> the grand Impoſtor, a flatterer of <hi>Capitoline Jove</hi> a Lyor, a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, and a Mad-Man. But (ſaith <hi>Paraeus</hi> in his foreſaid book, pag. 49. <hi>The Pope and the Church have not power to depoſe a King that is an Infidell; becauſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing ought to be according to the Laws. But the Laws do not grant this power to the Pope and to the Church, but to the Brethren of the Kingdome.</hi> (and as <hi>Danaeus</hi> hath it) <hi>it belongs to the godly States in every Common-wealth to chaſtiſe thoſe Kings which offend and depoſe thoſe which are obſtinate.</hi> The Pontificians againe cry out, a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, by whom he is ſtiled an Atheiſt a Politician, and Seditious; and affirme that this power of chaſtiſing Kings and depoſing them, doth no wayes properly belong to the Barons, or Peeres of the Kingdome or to the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, for the defect of coactive Juriſdiction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which Vaſſalls (for ſo they ſpeak) have not againſt their Lords. So <hi>Jaco. Anthon. Marta<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> de juriſdict. lib. 1. c. 23. num. 18. and <hi>Carerius</hi> de poteſt. Pontif. lib. 2. cap. 3. num. 6. Whether (Learned Sirs) will you have the Pope, or the Popular State, the Avenger and Judge of wicked Kings. Neither (I confeſſe ingeniouſly) doth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39316:50"/>pleaſe me. But that I may ingratiate my ſelfe into their favour, whom I ſo lately provoked, I ſuppoſe both opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions to be true, that all Kings Emperours and ſupreame Magiſtrates are obnoxious to the Pontifician, and to the Tribunitian Power. Yet that any man be juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, the courſe of the Court it ſelfe doth require theſe two things: the deſert of the Crime, and the order of Power, I would have thoſe Puritan-Papiſts to tell us, from whence this Pontificiall, and Popular power is.</p>
                  <p>Without doubt it is not from Chriſt, who yeilded both obedience and tribute to <hi>Tyberius Caeſar,</hi> no good Emperour; who reproved <hi>Peter</hi> ſmiting with the ſword and commanded him to put it up. Not from <hi>Paul</hi> who will have every ſoule ſubject to the higher Powers. Not from <hi>Peter</hi> who ſubjecteth all, without difference, to the King, and to thoſe (not Tribunes which are conſtituted by the People, not Legates which are ſent out from the Pope,) but Magiſtrates which are appointed by the King: from whence it neceſſarily followes; that all coactive power, and ſecular dignity doth iſſue from the King. whoſe ſacred Majeſty he that violates, ſhall be guilty of treaſon not ſo much againſt the humane as againſt the divine Majeſty, and what <hi>Bernard</hi> long ſince ſaid, <hi>(ad Archiepiſcop. Senonenſ.)</hi> may I now ſay to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty and Nobility; <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject; if every ſoule, then yours; who hath exempted you from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallity the that endeavours to exempt attempts to deceive; reſt not upon their councells who though they be Chriſtians, yet thinke it a diſgrace either to follow the example, or obey the precepts of Chriſt.</hi> Epiſt. 24.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="reason">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:39316:51"/>
                  <head>The ſixth Reaſon from the Authority of the Fathers.</head>
                  <p>In the primitive Church of an unſpotted faith, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with candid innocency, and purple Martyrdome there is a deepe ſilence of this power. Indeed thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients chooſe to ſuffer any thing for righteouſneſſe-ſake, and to be crowned with Martyrdome, rather than by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling violence with force, or by reſiſting publicke An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to be accounted guilty of impiety againſt God, or rebellion againſt the Emperours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his Apology for Chriſtians to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Pius</hi> deſcribes the duty of Subjects. <hi>That we may worſhip the true God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we willingly obey you Emperours, whom we acknowledge Kings and Princes, and we pray that there may appeare in you equall wiſdome joyned with your Royall Power.</hi> Tertullian alſo to Scapula Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of Carthage. <hi>Concerning the Majeſty of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour we are defamed, yet cannot the Chriſtians be found to be either Albinians, Nigrians, or Caſsians; a Chriſtian is no mans enemy, much leſſe the Emperors; whom (knowing him to be conſtituted by God) it is neceſſary that he reverence, and honour, and that he deſire his ſafety, with the whole Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empires, we reverence the Emperour therefore, as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to God; and what he is, he hath received from God, inferiour onely to God, &amp;c.</hi> The ſame Author in his Apologeticke relates the prayers and devotions of the Chriſtians; For the Emperour perſecuting the Church; <hi>The Chriſtians with their Arm's ſpread becauſe they are innocent, with their heads bared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bluſh not; laſtly from their hearts they pray for all Emperours, a long life, a ſecure Empire, a ſafe home, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39316:51"/>Armyes, a faithfull Senate, a loyall People, a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able World, and whatſoever is the deſire and wiſh of Man, and of Caeſar.</hi> The Founders of the Presbytery, were wont to pray otherwayes in Scotland. From the Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian blood good Lord deliver us. The moſt deſperate Contrivers of that Powder-Treaſon, prayed otherways in England, whom I think it were fit they were parg'd with Hellebore rather then refuted with Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Holy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſpeaking of the ſupreame Empery of Kings hath theſe words (<hi>ad Antioch. queſt.</hi> 55.) <hi>As God is King and Emperour over all the World, and doth excerciſe a power over all things which are in Heaven and in Earth; ſo is the Prince and King ſet over earthly things, who of his owne accord doth what he will, even as God himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The day would faile me if I ſhould recite to you the teſtimonies of <hi>Ignatius, Arnobius, Iraeneus, Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Ambroſe, Hierome, Baſil, Hillary, Chryſoſtome, Nazianzen, Cyrill, Optatus, Milevetanus, Leo</hi> the firſt, <hi>Fulgentius, Gregory</hi> the firſt, <hi>Bernard</hi> and others. And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhall be one for all, Epiſt. 42. (ad fratres <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daur.</hi>) <hi>Ye ſee the Temples of Idols, partly decayed without repaire, partly thrown down, partly ſhut up, partly changed to other uſes, and the Idols themſelves either broken, or burnt, or deſtroyed, and the very powers of this world, (which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time for theſe Idols ſake perſecuted the Chriſtian people) overcome and ſubdued by Chriſtians, not reſiſting but dying.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="reason">
                  <head>The ſeventh Reaſon from the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Proteſtants.</head>
                  <p>The Proteſtants vary not an haire's breadth from the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39316:52"/>Doctrin of the Ancient Church. Yet is it an uſuall thing with the Papiſts, to accuſe the Church (purg'd from the dregs of Popery) both, of defection from the Catholike Faith, and of Sedition in a conſtituted Polity. Hear from Cardinall <hi>Alanus</hi> the common calumny of the Papiſts (<hi>in reſponſ. ad Jnſtit. Brittan. c.</hi> 4. <hi>The Proteſtants</hi> (ſaith the Cardinall) <hi>deſperate and factious men, So long as they have Princes and Kings indulgent to their wills, they know well how to vſe that proſperous eſtate of Fortune but if their Princes croſſe their deſires, or the Laws be againſt them, preſently they breake the bonds of Loyalty, deſpiſe Majeſty every where, they rage with Slaughters, Firings, and Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, and run headlong into the contempt of all divine and humane things.</hi> Thus he. To the wiping off this foule calumny, I will ſet down a few ſayings of a few men, that the Adverſryes may bluſh, if they have not wholly caſt off all ſhame of Man, and feare of God. As for the followers of the Presbytery, I number them with the Jeſuits (whoſe manners they imitate) rather then with the Proteſtants, I call God to witneſſe, I never yet found any man devoted to the Idol of the Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, who was not as great an anemy to the Regall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as to the Epiſcopall Dignity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sleidan</hi> doth expreſſe the opinion of <hi>Luther</hi> at large, com. lib. 5. From whence I have taken theſe few words; <hi>No man</hi> (ſaith Luther) <hi>who moves Sedition can be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, although he have a juſt cauſe; he muſt repaire to the Magiſtrate, and attempt nothing privately. All Sedition is contrary to Gods precept, who diſalowes and deteſt's it.</hi> Thus he.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Philip Melancthon</hi> neither thought, nor ſpake other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes. <hi>Although it be the Law of Nature to repell force
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39316:52"/>with force; yet is it not lawfull by force to repell the force exerciſed by the Magiſtrate. Although we ſeeme to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe obedience, upon this condition, if the Magiſtrate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand things lawfull; yet is it not therefore lawfull to repell the unjuſt force of the Magiſtrate by force. Although Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires be obtained and poſſeſſed by wickedneſſe, yet the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naion of the Empire is the worke of God, and the good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God.</hi> There is therefore no force to be taken up againſt the Magiſtrate. Theſe words hath <hi>Melancthon</hi> in <hi>Luther,</hi> Tom. 1. pag. 463.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Brentius</hi> diſſents not from them, <hi>the Government of a Prince</hi> (as he hath it in Reſp. ad Art. Ruſtic.) <hi>may be evill two wayes. Firſt when any thing is commanded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Faith, as to renounce God. Here is the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtl's ſaying good, We muſt obey God rather than Man. Let not the Subject by any means uſe violence againſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; let him ſuffer any evill patiently, let him not ſtrike again, but be quiet, and ſuffer any diſcommodity rather than obey his wicked commande. Secondly the Government of a Prince may be evill, when any thing is commanded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to publike Juſtice; of which ſort is the exaction of a mans goods, or the puniſhing of his body; in thoſe kinds of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries Obedience becomes a Subject: for if he betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to Arms, his ſentence is paſt, he that ſmiteth with the ſword ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi> Thus Brentius</p>
                  <p>Under <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, <hi>Cranmer</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> together, with the Biſhops, and other the the more famous Divines of the Kingdome, in a booke concerning the Inſtitution of a Chriſtian man, hath theſe words. <hi>If Princes ſhall do contrary to what their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty requires, they have not in this world any Judge ſet over them by God; but are to render an account to God who hath
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39316:53"/>reſerv'd to himſelfe alone, the judgement of them. But it is horrible wickedneſſe for the Subjects to raiſe Sedition or Rebellion, although their Princes be evill. But God is to be pray'd unto, in whoſe hand are the hearts of Kings, that he would alluminate them by his Spirit, whereby they may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe the Sword committed to them, to Gods glory.</hi> Thus they.</p>
                  <p>Leaſt any man ſhould ſlanderouſly report that this was feigned, and therefore ſpoken to flatter the King; I will adde the opinions of others the moſt learned of that age; who lived under the Croſſe of Perſecution, who wrote in the troubleſome time of Baniſhment, and who ſuffered moſt cruell Death for the Truth of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>William Tyndall</hi> (an Exile for Religions ſake, and Martyr under <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth) put forth a Booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Chriſtian mans obedience in the nineteenth yeare of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight's Reigne, (when the Cardinall a Butchers Sonne led away the Lambs of Chriſt by flocks to the Slaughter) in which he deſcribes the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the King, and the duty of Subjects, according to the rule of the Goſpell. <hi>David</hi> (ſaith Tyndall) <hi>ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> Saul; <hi>if he had ſlayne him he had ſinned againſt God. In every Kingdome the King (who hath no Superiour) judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of all. He that attempts any miſchiefe to the Prince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Tyrant or Perſecutor, or with a ſtubborne hand touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Lords anoynted, is a Rebell againſt God, and reſiſts Gods Ordinance. As often as a private man offends, he is held guilty to the King, when the King offends he ought to be reſerv'd to the tryall and vengeance of God. And as it is not lawfull to reſiſt the King upon any pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſo is it not lawfull to riſe up againſt the Magiſtrate, who
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39316:53"/>is ſent by the King, to execute thoſe things which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the King.</hi> Thus he. <hi>Robert Barnes</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the fire in the year 1541. in a Tract concerning humane conſtitutions, he preſcribes the beſt forme of obedience to Subjects living under wicked Princes. <hi>If the King</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>endeavouring to root out the faith of Chriſt, ſhall forbid the hearing of the Word, or receiving of the Sacraments under the penalty of ſome great Fine, or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Death; God is to be called upon with faithfull prayers, the King petitioned with humble ſupplications, that he will be pleaſed to revoke his decree; if he will not doe it, it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a loyall Subject to cleave to the Truth, and patiently to bear the violence offer'd by the King. He that cannot fly a raging Perſecutor, let him patiently ſuffer the loſſe of goods, the tearing of his members; yea a Chriſtian ought to ſuffer moſt cruell death for the truth according to the example of Chriſt; whoſoever ſhall rebell for Religions ſake ſhall be guilty of eternall damnation.</hi> Thus Barnes.</p>
                  <p>They who in the Reigne of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> renounced Popery, &amp; refuſed to believe the breaden God, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to undergo the moſt exquiſite kinds of torments, &amp; after many Calamities, Miſeries, Chains, Fetters, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Thirſt; Cold and other Puniſhments, great without meaſure, many without number; being condemned to the Flames, they offered up their holy Soules an acceptable Sacrifice to God; of whom not any man either in his fore-ſpent life, or brought to the place of puniſhment being now laying down his life, did contemne the royall Majeſty, though ſo cruell. No man curſed the Queen (deſtroying her People the Church of God contrary to her publicke proteſtation) no man was found who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed obedience, yea no man who did not humbly pray
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39316:54"/>for her. So the Men of God, and dutifull Subjects by leaving to poſterity a famous example of obedience and patience, by leading an innocent life, free from ſedition, they ſealed with one and the ſame blood the duty of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and the purity of their faith.</p>
                  <p>We have not now place to ſpeak of the Proteſtants under <hi>Ferdinand, Maximilian,</hi> and <hi>Radolphus,</hi> Emperours of <hi>Germany,</hi> and under <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed memory Queen of <hi>England,</hi> (God I hope will grant an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) I cannot paſſe by one, anoynted by the Lord with the oyle of ſaving Grace, and ſingular Knowledge above his fellows, the pillar of the Church, the prop of the Common-wealth, a moſt expert Champion of Chriſt againſt Anti-Chriſt and the new Arrians, a moſt invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Warriour in the cauſe of Kings againſt the Papall Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, the Cardinall impoſtures, and Puritannicall ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; the reſtorer of the Epiſcopall Dignity, and moſt eager oppoſer of the Presbyteriall Anarchy, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor of the Catholick Faith, the truly peaceable King, in his golden treatiſe concerning the true Law of free Monarchy. pag. 48. <hi>The wickedneſſe of him that ruleth, ought not to ſubject the Ruler to them, over whom God hath appointed him to be Judge: if it be not lawfull for a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man to proſecute an injurie againſt a private Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, ſeeing God hath committed the ſword of Vengeance to the Magiſtrate alone; how much leſſe doſt thou think it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full either for all the people in generall, or ſome in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to uſurpe the ſword, (to which they have no right) againſt the publicke Magiſtrate, to whom alone it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi> Thus the moſt royall King.</p>
                  <p>Seeing the Papall and Tribunitian power is contrary to Nature, is diſalowed by the Law of Nations, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39316:54"/>and Cannon law; ſeeing it can find neither founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Word of God, nor patronage from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, nor entertainement with the moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Proteſtants; but is rejected, antiquated, and exploded by all with one mouth; I confidently aver, that it is the meer deviſe of Papiſts and Puritans, (ſeditious men) odious to God, injurious to Kings; deviſed to the ruine of the Common-wealth, and deſtruction of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Therefore I conclude according to the Dictate of Nature, the Law of Nations, the Civill and Canon Law, the ſacred Scriptures, the Orthodox Fathers, and moſt Famous Doctors of the Reformed Church. <hi>It is not lawfull to reſiſt the King violating the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Laws of the Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>1. Pet. 2.17.</bibl>
                        <p>Feare God, Honour the King.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
